<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Love to the lost: and a hand held forth to the helpless, to lead out of the dark. Wherein is plainly held out divers perticular things, as they are learned of Christ; and are most needfull to be known of all who profess godliness. Set forth chiefly for the directing the simple into the living way of truth, as it is in Christ Jesus, the Righteous, that therein they may come to the life and power of that which the world hath in words; which being received, satisfies the weary soul, and makes the creature wel-pleasing to his maker. Wherein also there is some reproofs to the dark world. / By one that seeks the redemption of Sions seed, and a lover of the creation of God, who is called James Naylor.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89843</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E866_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207630</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866669</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866669</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118947</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89843)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118947)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 131:E866[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Love to the lost: and a hand held forth to the helpless, to lead out of the dark. Wherein is plainly held out divers perticular things, as they are learned of Christ; and are most needfull to be known of all who profess godliness. Set forth chiefly for the directing the simple into the living way of truth, as it is in Christ Jesus, the Righteous, that therein they may come to the life and power of that which the world hath in words; which being received, satisfies the weary soul, and makes the creature wel-pleasing to his maker. Wherein also there is some reproofs to the dark world. / By one that seeks the redemption of Sions seed, and a lover of the creation of God, who is called James Naylor.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 4, 25 [i.e. 63], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black-spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 62 and 63 mismumbered '50' and '25' respectively.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "ffebr. 9. 1655"; also the last number of the imprint date has been marked through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118947:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Love to the Loſt: AND A HAND HELD FORTH To the Helpleſs, to lead out of the Dark. Wherein is plainly held out di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers perticular things, as they are learned of Chriſt; and are moſt needfull to be known in all who profeſſe godlineſs. Set forth chiefly for the direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Simple into the living way of Truth, as it is in Chriſt Jeſus, the Righteous, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they may come to the life and power of that which the World hath in words; which being received, ſatisfies the weary Soul, and makes the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture well-pleaſing to his Maker. <hi>Wherein alſo there is ſome Reproofs to the Dark World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By one that ſeeks the redemption of Sions Seed, and a Lover of the Creation of God, who is called <hi>JAMES NAYLOR.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle</hi> at the weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118947:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118947:2"/>
            <head>Let him that reads under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</head>
            <p>FRiends, The things following, which I have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of, are not things of Man, nor by Man did I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, but by the revelation of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which is contrary to the Wiſdom and Will of Man; Nor to the wiſdome and will of Man do I commend them to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; for the natural mans wiſdome receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, therefore would devour that which is born thereof: ſo, to that wiſdom I appear not, being a leight thing to me to be judged thereof: But if any one know the gift of God, and a meaſure of that Spirit, which openeth the boſome of the Father, and reveales his ſecrets unto Babes; The leaſt meaſure of that (if not clouded with the Imaginations) will ſavour theſe things; and to ſuch they may be profitable: So, to the light of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that which changeth not in every one, I appear to be judged and diſcerned, which is one in the Male and in the Female, for therein alone, both theſe things, and all other that proceeds from that root, makes for gathering Creatures together, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that One Name and Seed, wherein all the Nations of the earth are bleſſed: As therewith they are gathered into the one Word of Faith, and Power of Life, to believe and ſpeak the ſame things in the godly Converſation, which
<pb facs="tcp:118947:3"/>
leadeth to the end of all Rents, Schiſms, Hereſies, and Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Sects and Diviſions, into that one Name to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed where the fulneſs of God is, Bleſſed for ever.</p>
            <p>So, whoever thou art, that ſhall read theſe particulars fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, or any thereof, and ſhall find any thing, which for the preſent thou canſt not receive, be not haſty in judging that which yet thou know'ſt not, nor kick not againſt that, which comes contrary to thy will, leſt thou put far from thee in thy will, that, which therewith thou canſt not call again, and the day of thy viſitation paſs over unawares, and in the evil day thou be made to cry out, <hi>How have I hated Inſtruction, and reſiſted the day of Healing!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this know, that no Prophecie of old ever came by the will of man, nor by the will of man could be received; but by thoſe that ſtood in their own wills was ever reſiſted; And ſo muſt it be in theſe things, unleſs with the eye that never changeth thou read'ſt them: which if thou know'ſt ſuch a thing in thee, and ſtand ſingle therein, in the meek Spirit, not lifted up above thy meaſure, thou wilt come to feel how that of God in thee, anſwers to the things of God, as face anſwers face; and find them to agree with the life of the Scriptures, though for the preſent ſome things appear darkly; for to that Seed which is not of this world, which ſavours ſpiritually, and judgeth not according to outward appearance, is my ſervice. And to that of God in every Conſcience am I manifeſt, if therein I be received, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb facs="tcp:118947:3"/>
a good ſavour am I unto the Lord, in them that are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and in them that periſh, at that day when it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that I have not handled the Word of God deceitfully: Though, with the Swine who feeds on the Husk, this may be trampled on, and I ſought to be rent, if to ſuch it come to whom I ſend it not.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:118947:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118947:4"/>
            <list>
               <head>A Table of the ſeveral Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars following.</head>
               <item>Concerning the Fall of Man. Pag. I.</item>
               <item>Concerning Light and Life. p. 1.</item>
               <item>Concerning Righteouſneſſe. p. 3.</item>
               <item>Concerning the Word. p. 8.</item>
               <item>Concerning Worſhip. p. 8.</item>
               <item>Concerning Errour, Hereſie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 11.</item>
               <item>Concerning Faith. p. 13.</item>
               <item>Concerning Hope. p. 15.</item>
               <item>Concerning Love. p. 17.</item>
               <item>Concerning Judgment. p. 19.</item>
               <item>Concerning Perfection. p. 21.</item>
               <item>Concerning Government, or Magiſtracy. p. 24.</item>
               <item>Concerning Obedience. p. 27.</item>
               <item>Concerning good Works. p. 29.</item>
               <item>Concerning Election and Reprobation. p. 32.</item>
               <item>Concerning the New Birth. p. 34.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:118947:5"/>Concerning the Baptiſm of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> from that the World ſo calls. p. 37.</item>
               <item>Concerning the Lords Supper. p. 43.</item>
               <item>Concerning Redemption. p, 47.</item>
               <item>Concerning Juſtification, Sanctification, and Mortification. p. 50.</item>
               <item>Concerning the Law. p. 52.</item>
               <item>Concerning <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> p. 56.</item>
               <item>Concerning the Miniſtry of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> p. 59.</item>
               <item>Concerning Free-Will. p. 62.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="I" facs="tcp:118947:5"/>
               <head>Concerning the Fall of Man.</head>
               <p>IN the beginning God made all things good, ſo did he Man, whom then he made in his own Image, and placed in him his own Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Power, whereby he was compleatly furniſhed with Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, Power, and Authority, over the Works of Gods hands, knowing the nature and uſe of each Creature, by what God had placed in him of Himſelf; who in that ſtate was the Son of God, whoſe ſeed was in himſelf. God alſo made the Tree of Life in the mid'ſt of the Garden, and the Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil, and both of theſe was good in their place; but the Tree of Knowledge, not good for food: Therefore did he that made it forewarn of it, as the thing wherein death was placed, as in the other Tree, was Life: And herein was the Bleſſing and the Curſe placed; the Life and the Death; the Obedience and the Diſobedience, Election and Reprobation: And this was good for man in their place, whilſt man ſtood in his place, guided by that which placed him in the good, and fore-warned him of the knowledge, and gave him power againſt it, whilſt he ſtood in that Wil, which had ſet all theſe things in their place, which Will was free for God, and from ſinne; and the will of God, and the will of Man was one, and ſo at unity with all the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But when man looked out into the other, where he ruled who abids not in the Truth, wherein the diſobedience was received in, of that which was contrary to the will of God to feed upon, then he joyned to that which was contrary, wherein the weakeneſſe was, and the death, darkneſſe, and blindneſſe, as to the things of God; and that which freely
<pb n="II" facs="tcp:118947:6"/>
he had received of God: And grew ſubtil within himſelf, and wiſe to do evil, ſo that he had loſt the will that was free, to wait upon God in his wiſdome and counſel, freely to be cared for by him, and ſo from the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe and innocency, and pure wiſdome and ſpiritual power, which God had placed in his heart, he fell, and into the ſelf-inventions which he had choſen in the contrary will; and ſo entring into the forbidden thing became accurſed, loſt the meaſure of God, his honour and likeneſſe, in which he ſtood above the Creation, and ſo became bruitiſh in his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; and, as to the things of God, as the Beaſt that periſh, for the Seed he had loſt, wherein the Election, the Wiſdome, the Authority, and all haopineſſe, preſent and eternal, did conſiſt, and ſo became led by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Seed, wherein God had placed emptineſſe of himſelf, which he had raiſed up for diſhonour: And here it is that man hath loſt his domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over the Devil, by letting him in, which otherwiſe had never power further then to proffer; which now being got in with a ſhew of God and godlineſſe into the Temple of God, the principle part in man; and man having joyned in one with him now is become his Captive, in whom he makes havock, beguiling him of the life of ſimplicity and godlineſſe, and perverting his ways, as to the end for which man was made; yea, all the mercies that God gives to that Creature, he being above, and Ruler in the heart, are turned to the Luſt that is Carnal and Self-ended; and to that Luſt and Self-ended things the man becomes a Servant; yea, hath ſo loſt his dominion, as he is brought to ſerve the Creature, over which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as Ruler<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hence it is, that ſome become ſervants, and are captivated; ſome with Covetouſneſſe; ſome with Pride; ſome with Luſt; and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeveral things, which are become Lords in the heart of man, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is hurried with all eagerneſſe out of all moderation, hunting after vanity and folly; yea, what vain toyes and fooliſh trifles hath led away the heart of man from the pure wiſdom of his God, till he ſcarce knows any end of running after changable things, gluttony and exceſſe in dyet yet not ſatisfied, foolery in apparel, without all ſtay or ſtop, being whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fallen from that which is unchangable, the true ſatisfaction and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and the further man goes in this ſtate, the more emptineſſe and darkneſſe comes in upon himſelf; and being fallen under the earthly principle, he is covered with thick darkneſſe, ſo that the mind of God he knows not, nor his woful ſtate he ſees not, the God of this world having blinded the eye, which ſhould ſhow him his miſery; and the ear being ſtopt, which ſhould hear the voyce of the ſouls ſhepheard, whereby he ſhould be quickned, his eye and ear being led out to Carnall things, and there captivated, ſo that the voyce of the Spirit he knowes not. And ſo being become heart-blind, cannot receive the way in Spirit, and whatſoever is ſpoken to man in this ſtate, in love to the ſoul which lies in death, the Serpent being above upon the earth, catcheth the thing into the Imaginations; and the Creature being led to conſult with him there in the fleſh, he beguils the Creature of the ſimplicity, and keeps the
<pb n="III" facs="tcp:118947:6"/>
Creature ſo in Self, that he regards not the Seed of God which is fallen under all this death and darkneſſe; and ſo long as the Creature will but hearken to him, and his lying promiſes, he will lead him from one thing to another, in things without; but never to ſee that from whence he is faln. Therefore, to all in this ſtate, Chriſt and all his Miniſters preached repentance, that all might turn their minds from theſe dead works to the living God, who is a Spirit known in Spirit, and ſo worſhipped, whoſe Kingdom is within, and whoſe light is in the midſt of all this darkneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though the darkneſſe comprehend it not; but as many as repen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of their following this way of ſelf-wiſdom and knowledge, and come to ſtand ſtill, to ſuch he ſhows his Salvation, and his Kingdome near at hand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which the Serpent, whilſt they follow him, doth put afar off: And as the mind is ſtaid to wait for the Kingdome of God in Spirit, the god of the world comes to be denied and reſiſted; And as the mind is ſtaid in the light from hearkning to the earthly: So that Seed which lies in Death, comes to hear the voyce of the Sonne of God, and to receive life and ſtrength from the Word, whereby it is raiſed out of the grave, and appears above the earth, to receive from the Father the dew of heaven whereby it is nouriſhed and refreſhed; and as man beholds the Seed growing, ſo he comes to ſee the new Creation, and what he loſt in the Fall, and ſo is reſtored by the power of the Word in the Son of God, into his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, power, and purity, made able to reſiſt the Devil; to chuſe the thing that is good, and delight in it, as before he delighted in the contrary: ſo comes man to be reconciled to his Maker, in the Eternal Unity beyond what is to be expreſſed; The wiſdome and power received from above, whereby the heart is ſet free from Corruption, and made able to eſcape the pollutions of the world, and to run the pure ways with delight, which is the glorious liberty of the Sons of God, the reſurrection from the dead, and the entrance into the everlaſting reſt.</p>
               <p>And now all you who find your ſelves fallen from your Dominon, that meaſure of God which he placed in man, from which he received power and wiſdome over the evill one; and now find your ſelves led Captive with the evil one, into the ways of Death, Sinne, and Evill: ſo that Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption hath got dominion in you, and over you; never look to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by that which leads out, for that which acts in the fleſh is onely evill, and will but lead you from Mountain to Hill, and ſo keep you doing without in ſelf, without life and power, healing your ſelves in falſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, which will not ſtand in ſtead in the evil day, nor reconcile to God to be accepted in any thing you do; for that is the firſt man with his righteouſneſſe. But to that from which you are fallen muſt you look, &amp; return into that from which you are gone out, that by the light thats in the midſt of all this darknes and death, you may be led in again by the blood of the Croſs, through the fire and ſword, into the Garden of God
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118947:7"/>
where he plants and feeds, into which the old man, with his will and works, cannot enter, nor he whoſe Leader is any viſible thing; for by the Spirit from whence man is fallen and gone out, by the ſame muſt he be led in again; and that ſeed which man hath ſinned againſt, muſt make the atonement, to which the Promiſe is, which is free, and ſets all free as they were born thereof: So that which leads out into the Knowledge, is the Fall; but that which leads into the Simplicity of Life, which is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in the Spirit, and not in the Knowledge of the firſt man, that leads to the Reſurrection of Life; for it is the hidden wiſdome, that God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained before the world unto glory: So to the hidden man of the heart muſt you look to find it, which is not Corruptible.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118947:7"/>
               <head>Concerning <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Life.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GOd is the life of every Creature, though few there be that know it; for the darkneſſe ſees him not, nor his life, though the Children of Darkneſſe have got words in the Scripture (which were given forth from the light) to talk of, yet God ſuch know not preſent: for the firſt beginning of God in the world is lighr; <hi>God ſaid, let there he light, and it was ſo.</hi> And this light God ſaw that it was good: This is that which was in the beginning with God, the Word, by which all things were made and ſeen; and without this was nothing made that was made, nor any thing ſeen to be good; and darkneſſe was over the face of all the waters till the light, which from the Word came, who is the Life; which life is the light of men: So none can ſee the life, but with the light, which from the life comes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which to the life leads all that follow it. So this that was in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, is given to keep in order all the Creation: <hi>That is good;</hi> but the darkneſſe comprehends it not, though it ſhine in it: ſo all that abide in the darkneſſe are deſtroyed, not diſcerning the life, to order and govern the Creation in the light.</p>
               <p>So all that go out of the light, go into the darkneſſe, and there the life and Image of God is loſt, and there is the Fall, and all who there abide are reſerved in Chaines of darkneſſe, not knowing the life which breaks the Bonds and Chains of Iniquity, and opens the Grave and Priſon door. And here the Soul being in death, breathing after the Life, but Darkneſſe got above: In the darkneſſe is the Creature led into Sects, Opinions, and Errours, after the Imaginations, to ſeek life; but further it runs here to the ſenſuall Wiſdome, further into Death and Darkneſſe, till the Creature be ſo blinded in the underſtanding, that he thinks and imagins he doth God ſervice, when he is acting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the life of God, both in himſelf, and others: ſo comes the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God and his Life, wherewith God did furniſh him to do his Will wholly to be loſt, and the Goſpel hid, that ſhould recover him again; the God of this World having ſo blinded the mind, and thereby ſo farre
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118947:8"/>
alienated him from the life of God, that he neither hath power and life to do the will of God, nor light to know where to have it yet in this condition of death, and darkneſſe, and without the: life of God ſhall the Creature never be without profeſſion, or ſome conceit or other, to keep in a vain hope of ſalvation.</p>
               <p>And here is the ſole ground and cauſe why we have ſo many ſorts of, formes and opinions, and wayes of worſhip, but none that doth good, nor lives in what they ſay, becauſe all have loſt the life of God which onely is able to bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g forth the righteouſneſſe of God. And ſelfe hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing got the form, into the Imagination above the life, cannot receive the light that l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es under, that condemns it. So all the world lies in darkenſſe, yea thick darkneſſe is upon all the ſeas, and great depths is covered with groſſe darkneſſe: and from thence is the Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſpread over all; so that none can witneſſe the work of God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knows the beginning nor end thereof. And this is the cauſe of condemnation, and it reſts upon all who are out of the life of God. And no other way there is appointed of the Father, to come out of this condition, but Chriſt Jeſus, the light and life of men; who is the light that is in the world, though the world know him not; which light ſhines in darkneſſe, but cannot therewith be comprehended; which light is the revealer of darkneſſe, and manifeſts the deeds thereof, and the firſt appearance of this in the Creature, ſhews the darkneſſe, and captivity that is in the darkneſſe; till which the Creature never comes to ſee the wretched condition that man is in, who is without God the life; nor till then will the Creature be willing to ſtand ſtill to ſee Gods ſalvation; but is full with vain hopes, conceits, and Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and the vaile is over the heart, and what God hath there written is not ſeen, and ſo being whole needs not the phyſitian. And with this blind heart the creature reads the Scriptures, and ſteals the promiſes that the Children of light ſpoke of who had the life, whereby the ſeed was raiſed out of the grave, to which the promiſe is; but neither knowes law nor Goſpel; neither came ſo far as <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet boaſting of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But when the light is minded, the Creature comes to ſee death raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſelf alive without the law, with that light which was given to keep out of the pollution, and defilements; and ſo to keep the life clear and unſpotted. With that light, that is ſeen and judged which hath paſſed over the life and defiled it, and that which hath gendered to bondage is ſeen, and the hardneſſe of heart comes to be felt, and the cauſe ſeen, even the great transgreſſion of the pure law; &amp; ſo comes the fear of the God, to take hold of the man that hath lived out of the life of God, and taketh pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe; and the Creature then finds trouble within, even where the ſtrong man did keep the houſe in peace; and abiding in the light, the cauſe and end of it is ſeen, and d welling in the fear; Wiſdom is received from
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118947:8"/>
above to depart from the iniquity; and in departing from the iniquity, there is a coming nearer to God; ſo the light growes, and ſprings; as there is a comming nearer of the juſt paths of life. And as the light ariſeth the Creation is ſeene, and how the enmity hath ſpread over, and how the luſt hath defiled it, and how that which was planted as a vineyard is become as a wilderneſſe for barrenneſs growne over with thornes and bryars, ſturdy Oaks, and tall Cedars, for want of the Vinedreſſer: and where the Lilly ſhould grow, its growne over with Weeds, Thiſtles, and Nettles; ſo that God walks not there becauſe of the great abomination; and that is the cauſe of all your woe, even his abſence.</p>
               <p>And when you ſee this the lamentation begins, in the houſe of laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, even after him from whom you have fallen; and as you follow the light, and come nearer to the Lord from whence it comes, you will ſee that it is onely your own wills, and wayes that hath ſeparated you from the holy one. And with the light you will come to ſee, how often you have beene moved by the ſpirit of light, from your evill wayes; and that the cauſe why you have beene thus long in the Fall, hath beene in ſelfe-will, and worldly pleaſures, whereby the life hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered: never till then comes any to ſee him whom you have peirced, nor to lament over him, nor to ſee what it is that oppreſſeth the juſt, nor to hate that which God hates, and love that which he loves, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny meaſure; but joynes with that which deſtroyes the ſoul, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voures the life; and yet makes a profeſſion, and a prayer againſt it in words; and thats the phariſee, and hypocrite, who with the words de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys the life, who makes a profeſſion above the life, but not in the life; and this is he that climeth up ſome other way, then the life which is the doore, to which the light leads. And in this ſtate are all the high minded, lofty ones, whoſe mouths ſpeake of great things, ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling words of vanity; for ſo are words without life; empty Braſſe, giving a pleaſant voyce to the carnall eare, but cannot evidence the life, and the works of it; who have the Saints words preſent, but their righteouſneſſe is as far off as <hi>Judea, Corinth, Theſſalonica,</hi> &amp;c: and theſe are they who in words confeſſe God, but in works deny him who have a large faith in words, but to the good worke reprobate: for none can be of any true judgment concerning the work of God, who are ſtrangers to the life that workes it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Righteouſneſs.</head>
               <p>THat Righteouſneſs which God accepts is but one, which is his own; perfectly fulfilled, and manifeſt in the world in Chriſt Jeſus the light, and Saviour thereof; which Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is not of the world, nor manifeſt to the world, nor in the world received, but by the world ever Judged as unrighteouſneſs; nor can the world inherit it; but only they who believe in the light of Chriſt, which God hath given into the world
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118947:9"/>
to lead out of the world, to Chriſt, where Gods righteouſneſs is. And there be many talkers of this righteouſneſs, but none inherit it, further then by faith they receive the Son of righteouſneſs; and with him his righteouſneſs is freely imputed, or put into the creature, a free gift from the Father; and with this righteouſneſs is the creature made righteous even as he is righteous, even as the meaſure of Chriſt is received, and no further; and whoſe life is kept in the meaſure of him, as he is ſo are we in this preſent world, and not of this world, even as he is of not of this world: and herein is boldneſs in the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in that which is perfect. And all that is not perfect, is ſelf and with the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, denied in the light; which condemns all ſelf-actings, under what pretence ſoever.</p>
               <p>So who abides in the righteouſneſs, abides in that which denies Self, and all the world; and ſo lives in obedience to that which is contrary to all mens wills, and ſo every where evil-ſpoken on; for the will of men works not the righteouſneſs of God: but this righteouſneſs is wrought into the Creature, in that obedience which is contrary to the will of the fleſh; and in the faith, by the eternall Spirit, is the new begetting both of the will and the deed: and ſo the new is born of the Spirit and life. And ſo farr as any have this righteouſneſs, he doth not lye under ſin, nor give place to the Divell, but it is as a breſt-plate, againſt all aſſaults, on the right hand, and on the left: and all who have not this, are they who have that which will not ſtand in ſtead in the evil day. So you that ſay, your righteouſneſs is as filthy Raggs, why do you abide in that? Gods righteouſneſs is not ſo: wherefore, Ceaſe from that, and own that which is perfect; even that everlaſting righteouſneſs, in which his all Saints have been gathered unto himſelf; who can receive nothing but whats his own; and it muſt be yours alſo, elſe can you not be received in it. In vain do you plow wickedneſs, and ſow iniquity, and think to reap righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>So with the light you may ſee what works in you, and to what you yeeld your ſelves ſervants to. That you bring forth while you live, that will go with you: ſo if you own no works in you, but what God works, you ſhall have no righteouſneſs but what is perfect, even the leaſt meaſure of it. And as you obey unto this righteouſneſs, you ſhall ſee the Spirituall man raiſed, and living, and the bonds of death broken, and that living which gives power over hell and death. Then may you ſay the ſpirit is life becauſe of righteouſneſs: and your dead profeſſion will be Judged with the life, as it ariſes; and ſeen to be fruitleſs.</p>
               <p>But this is blaſphemy in your own eyes, who have made Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs a cover for your abominations. What wickedneſs is ſo vile now in theſe nations, but the righteouſneſs of Chriſt is made a Cover? &amp; men bleſſe themſelves there-with, in the greateſt abomination: And this hath its beginning at the head of deceit, and is gone over all the whole body. For to cover your own wickedneſs, pride, and covetuouſneſs, have you teachers invented this faith: That its ſufficient to believe in a righteouſneſs you read of in the letter, through you be not obedient
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118947:9"/>
to it in Spirit. But you that are not ſervants of Righteouſneſſe, are no ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Chriſts, and his Workes; and your Faith, without his Works, will be little worth to Salvation; and even as it ſaves you out of ſinne, ſo will it ſave you out of condemnation, and no further; And this, that in your Conſcience will witneſſe, if you take counſel at it, no further then you find the power of his righteouſneſſe working in you, and you owning it in obedience, and ſubjection, and joyning to it againſt all unrighteouſneſſe; no more of it you can inherit, nor be made the righteouſneſſe of God in him.</p>
               <p>And at that day when he comes to ſeparate the precious from the vile, then will you ſee in what ſtead your notions of righteouſneſs are, when the Worker of iniquity is found, and judged with Chriſts righteouſneſſe, of which you have been boaſting in words without the power of it: By the power and purity of it, ſhall all the workers of iniquity be judged, and condemned. So, deceive not your ſelves, He that workes righteouſneſs is righteous, even as he is righteous; but he that talks of this, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits ſin, is of the Devil; and with him, muſt inherit, by whom he is acted, and guided: for Gods righteouſneſs will not mixe with, nor cover deceipt, nor was it ever given for that purpoſe; but as it is obeyed, it reveales, and deſtroys mans righteouſneſs, and unrighteouſneſſe, as it is revealed from Faith to Faith, by which the juſt lives, and the unjuſt periſheth, and paſſeth into death. And all who have Chriſts righteouſneſſe, can witneſſe this effect, to kill and make alive, as by Faith it is received; and this is Zions righteouſneſſe that goes forth as brightneſſe, and the Salvation thereof as a Lamp that burneth, that the Gentiles may ſee it, and its glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>Be aſhamed you Heathens, who have hid the Lords righteouſneſſe under your Pride and Covetouſneſſe; who have exalted the Idols of the World and bring forth to the Oppreſſor; who have bowed down to the god of this World, and his begettings are in all houſes, and aſſemblies, and the name of the Lord you have polluted before all the world; yet will you lean upon the Lord, and ſay, The righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt; ſo that you have more diſhonoured his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, then all that ever were before you: and the name of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is become a reproach in all the world, becauſe of your unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to his righteouſneſſe. For this, will he plead with you, and will take from you the Covering, that you may appear; and he will bring forth his Righteouſneſſe to your Confuſion; and his own ſhall witneſſe him in the Gate; and his work ſhall praiſe him openly: ſo ſhall ſinners be afraid, and fearfulneſſe ſurprize the Hypocrite, when God ſhall own his own righteouſneſſe, and judge the wicked after the works of their hands.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118947:10"/>
               <head>Concerning the Word.</head>
               <p>THe Word is that which was in the beginning, and was the beginning of all viſible things, and that by which all things were made, but it ſelf is inviſible<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which, though it be the Upholder of all viſible things, yet can no viſible thing reveal it; yet doth it reveal the ground, and uſe, and end of all viſibles. And as without it was nothing made, that was made; ſo without it, is nothing ſoen, as it was made, nor any thing can be guided, nor uſed in its pure place; but what ever man medles with, not having the Word in him, to guide, order, and ſanctifie the ſame, he defiles, and it is polluted as to him. Nor can this Word be comprehended in Heaven or Earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> without this Word can no Scripture be read with profit; for it opens the Scriptures, and the Scriptures declare of it; yet cannot the Scriptures, nor all the Writings of the World comprehend it, nor declare the depth and extent of it, which is beyond all Generations; yet is it the Teacher and Guide of his own in all Generations; and in all Generations of Saints hath been known in meaſure, more or leſſe immediatly, though it hath no place in the worlds profeſſion.</p>
               <p>So hearing of a Word but not knowing it, they ſay The Letter is it. But who hath the Word, hath that which comprehends Death, and Hell, and the Grave; that which binds and chains Satan, overcomes the World, gives the iſſues of Life, and Light, whereby the new Creation is known wherein dwels Righteouſneſſe; and this every one hath, ſo far as he hath the Word abiding in him; but ſo hath not every one that hath the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Nor can any mans will change the Word, for it is contrary to all mens Wills; nor can any mans Wit open or expound this Word, which confounds the Wiſdome of the Wiſe, and brings the underſtanding of the Prudent to nought; that hides from the Wiſe and Prudent, and reveals to Babes; and the Word grows and increaſes within the Babes, but ſo doth not the Letter; and as it grows, it ſanctifies all that have it, but ſo doth not the Letter: and its as a Fire and a Hammer to all that have it, but ſo is not the Letter: It is quick and powerful, to the dividing aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Joynts and Marrow, the Soul and Spirit, where ever it is; ſo is not the Letter: And the Word is a Reproach to every Carnal Mind, even to them eſpecially who profeſs the Letter. Whoſoever have the Word, with it are waſhed, and cleanſed, and tranſlated from the World, and confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to God, ſo far as they have it, and it reconciles to God all that have it; but many have the Letter, who know not God, but are in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Cuſtomes, and Faſhions, and wayes of the World, not changed, nor reconciled.</p>
               <p>None can keep the Word and his ſins both, but the Letter without he may, for where ever the Word is known, the new Creature is witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118947:10"/>
who is created to walk in Righteouſneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and who hath the Word ſees all, who ſay they know the Word and walk not in Righteouſneſſe, to be Lyars, and do not the Truth; and with the Word of Truth are ſuch caſt out, and judged to be thoſe who diſhonour the Word, as though it were a polluted thing, or could dwell with pollution; which is a Fire to burn up all uncleanneſſe, where ever it is; and where ſinne ſtands, the Word is not known.</p>
               <p>But ſuch, reading of the word, which came to the Saints (in obedience to which they were waſhed and purified, and in which they were begotten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain) they finding that the Saints had this word, but not knowing it, they ſay the Letter is it; which doth but declare of it: and ſo their word hath not power in them to overcome the Devil, &amp; break the bonds of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereas the word of God is not bound, but free, &amp; ſets free all that have it abiding in them; which breaks down the ſeat of ſin; and raiſes up, and quickens the ſeed of God, which lives in the life of God, (which through ſin, death hath paſſed over) and ſo quickens the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall body to newneſs of life. So that the old life and the word cannot ſtand together in one body; nor doth the old man who lives in that life know any word, but the letter, and the life of that he knows not; but in the Imaginations ſearches with the fallen wiſdome for that which God hath in his wiſdome hid from it; and in this is all the darkneſſe: to this the Scriptures are ſpoken as a Parable and Myſtery; which in that diſobedient wiſdome cannot be found out: ſo is the Simplicity deceived with Meanings, Addings, and Wreſtings, which are all in that man that cannot enter, in whom the Word dwells not, nor can any thing ſuch do be accepted, becauſe it is not from the Word; for all that comes not from the Word, by the Word is condemned, not to be the Work of God; for all that God made, he made it by the Word, and it was ſeen in the light to be good which was made with the Word, and here all ſtood in the reconciliation to God; but when man went out from the Word, then he went out from the good, and ſo with the Light was ſeen to be in the evil, and ſo was accurſed from the ſame Word againſt which he had ſinned; and ſo long<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as out of that Word he acts, all is accurſed, being Self, and not God, that works it.</p>
               <p>And ſo man being gone out into the world, the light of the Goſpel is preached to turne man again to know the word, that coming to the knowledge thereof in his heart, and having his mind ſtayed thereto, in the light, he may come to ſee the power of the word working in Spirit, working<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> out the unclean nature and the rebellious will, and working in the pure nature, in the Croſs ſlaying the carnall man with all his affections, and ſo through death thereof raiſing up the new man, making a new Creation, in Chriſt Jeſus, with power unto Good works from the eternall word: and this God owns when he is the mover there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of and worker alſo, and the creature only ſervant therein in the ſame power. And this is not a ſelf, taken on performance from the Letter, but is in the eternall counſell and ſtrength of God, commanded, moved, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118947:11"/>
performed in Gods will and time, &amp; contrary to the will of the fleſh, whereby the will of all fleſh is ſubdued, even all that is come in ſince the beginning, till all be ſeen in the light to be good, and the work of God: and ſo his works praiſe him, from a good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the ſpirit, and power of the Living God. And with the living word is the living ſoul witneſſed, and the life of Chriſt made manifeſt, in the mortal body, and the creature comes to have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the life, and is transformed thereinto, and united in one; and this is the word of reconciliation which unites God and the Creature in Spirit; which who ever knows needs not go forth for wiſdom counſell or ſtrength, againſt all the powers of darkneſs, nor wiles of the enemy, but by diligent taking heed to the word which is nigh in the heart, from thence finds the iſſues of life, ſpiritual ſtrength, and power againſt the ſpiritual wickedneſs, which all who run out for help, lye under &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſervants of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Worſhip.</head>
               <p>THe worſhip of the true and living God ſtands out of mans will, and knowledge, wiſdom or prudence, as in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall; for God is a Spirit, and in Spirit he is worſhipped not with mens hands, nor with bodily exerciſe, further then by the eternall Spirit the body is exerciſed; nor doth it ſtand in meats and drinks, nor divers waſhings, nor carnall ordinances taken on by tradition, nor imitation of others; but as every Creature is moved by the Spirit of the living God, who is that Spirit, who will be ſerved with his own alone, not with any thing in man, which is come in ſince the fall; ſo the imaginations, thinkings, and conceavings are ſhut out; all mans ways, mans times, and formes, nationall cuſtomes, mans decency, and orders, by men deviſed, and added, are all ſhut out, and condemned with that Spirit in which God alone is worſhipped, and his people taught his worſhip, and the manner of it; and the times are in his hand, whoſe the worſhip is.</p>
               <p>So that before any can rightly worſhip God, they muſt waite to know his Spirit, that leads to know him and his worſhip, and the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and manner: for all who do the ſame thing as to the outward per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, do not worſhip God, becauſe they worſhip not in Spirit, and power of God himſelfe: So that all who would ſo worſhip him as to be accepted, you muſt know the light, and in it waite to know what God calls for at your hands: for it is not what men appoint you to do, or not to do, that will acquit you before the Lord: for this know, that God made man for himſelfe, and for his ſervice, and the living God, is not as the dumbe Idolls, that people ſhould imagine a way to ſerve him as may beſt ſute with the faſhion and cuſtome of a Nation, or people, but he that made man hath given him a life from himſelf to improve in his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118947:11"/>
ſervice, and a light hath he given wherewith to ſee the moving of this Spirit of life, which ever moves after the will of God, becauſe it is of him; and ſo where it is awakned it ever draws the Creature to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God; the mind, and will, and affections, and love of God is in it; and who walks in the light ſees this: But the Creature running before this or without this, there comes all the dead works and worſhips. And the ground of all this ariſeth out of darkneſs and diſobedience, for when the Creature hath beene out, in the world, and unrighteous wayes thereof, doing that which is evill, then that in the heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns for the evill, and neglect of good; then the ſame mind runs to act a worſhip to get peace, when both the evill, and the worſhip is in one nature, and ſo the prayer becomes abomination, as the others was, for he that regards the iniquity, God will not heare his prayers, nor accept his worſhips; that's <hi>Cains</hi> ſacrifice, and <hi>Eſaus</hi> prayers; but either muſt your worſhip be performed in one that never ſinned, or it cannot be accepted with the pure God.</p>
               <p>So that the way to be well pleaſing to the Father, is to waite in the light till you ſee ſomthing of the Spirit of life which is in Chriſt Jeſus moving in you, and then to that joyne in its power to worſhip; and that being of God he cannot forget himſelfe; and that is done in the name of Chriſt which is done in his light, and power, and wiſdom, and ſtrength; and what ever is done in his name is not denyed of the Father; and ſo far as any are in him, ſo far ſons, and ſo far accepted in him; without whom you can doe nothing, nor be reſpected; nor did ever any worſhip in this nature but they found acceptance, and the knowledge thereof, and you who know not this to lead and guide you in your worſhips, are worſhiping you know not what, nor with what<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and though you ſay, that God works all your works in you, and that it is his work, and worſhip you are about; yet when it comes upon try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all he will not own it for his, which the worker of iniquity hath wrought. For the evil worker hath not onely his hand in the deceitfull works of the unrighteous Mammom, but in the deceitfull works of Worſhip too. For did he not deceive in worſhip, to hide his wickedneſſe, with pretence of godlineſſe, and long prayers, he could not keepe people in any peace in his wicked wayes: ſo they who joyne to him herein, receive the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter damnation, for the falſe worſhippers were alwayes greateſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Chriſt, and ſo to their own ſouls, and woe to him that hides his ſin thus.</p>
               <p>So all who deſire to worſhip in truth, you muſt know the truth, even the Spirit of truth, to lead into all truth; which Spirit of truth takes of Chriſt, and teſtifies of his life, and power, in the Creature worſhiping, who believes in the light; and ſuch know they are in him, and he in them, who is true, in whom they worſhip the Father of the truth, and ſo God is ſerved with his own; and no further then this is known, can any worſhip God in Spirit; which the light doth manifeſt. So you having received a light from Chriſt, in that waite, till therein you find the Spirits leading, acting, and ordering: and here the leaſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118947:12"/>
in the light, is in Gods ſervice, when on him you are waiting in Spirit and ſuch as abide in the light, waiting upon God, in the light, are kept from ſerving the Prince of darkneſſe, and having your loynes gire and your light burning, you are always ready to know the voyce, and anſwer it with obedience, and then you ſerve God and not men, when you have a command from the living God, not taken on by tradition from men; for in vaine do all worſhip, whoſe feare and ſervice towards God is taught by the precepts of men; for all the Children of the Lord are taught of the Lord: And they are the Sons of God, who are led by the Spirit of God: and ſuch harken to the Lord and know his voyce; and what they ſee and heare, that they doe, and doe not offer the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of fools.</p>
               <p>But do not you ofter the ſacrifice of fooles, who have been worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all your time, and yet have his worſhip to learne? and are but ſtill asking, If this be the right worſhip, and have it yet to diſpute? (if not confident in a falſe way; which is much worſe): and ſuch are you who are fighting, and contending for ſuch a manner of worſhip as Chriſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ordained, nor his own ever practiſed; as you may ſee, if you compare your nationall worſhip, with the Saints practice; which is changed in every particular, and that by men and councels, under pretence of decency or conformity, or ſomthing that ſtands in mens will which God never commanded. But you may long worſhip here, and call it Gods worſhip, ere he own it by anſwering you, yet was <hi>Nebuchad nezzer</hi> never more zealous for his Image, then you are for this, if you had but his power; yea them who have found the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting way of Chriſt, and an anſwer from God in it, ſuch would you force to bow to your imaginations, where you know not God nor his preſence, with you therein; nor can you euer find God in that way which is not his own, nor is that his own which generations of men, and councels have altered, and added to and changed, from time to time, as may moſt ſute their cuſtomes and Countryes; ſo that each Nation hath its different manner of worſhip, but all out of the counſel of God, agreed on by Councels of men.</p>
               <p>And all you who are gone out in any thing from Chriſt the true pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne and example, you are gone into the imaginations of men, and ſo are become ſervants of men, and not of God, herein. For God is pure and ſo is his way, and worſhip, and without his command cannot be changed in the leaſt jot, but by him is denyed, and is become will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip, and not Gods worſhip: For it is not the name that makes it Gods worſhip, for all pretend to worſhip God; but it is the nature of it, which muſt be in Spirit and will of God, contrary to the will of all men, and their wiſdome, wherein men in all ages have performed the idolatrous worſhip, and ſet up likeneſſes inſtead of true worſhip; though being heart-blind did not know it, but ever looked upon all to be out of the way but themſelves. And this is your work who at this day ſet up an imitation from the letter of what other men have done, but have not received your command and power in Spirit from the Lord and to you it will be ſaid, Who hath required theſe things at your hands?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118947:12"/>
for all the Saints have their commands in Spirit, but yours is in letter and ſo of another Miniſtration; for the litterall Miniſtration is don away in the ſpirituall; and all that knows the command in Spirit, knows it is life eternall, and gives life to fulfill the command, and ſo the worſhip is ſpiritual; and the heart, and the mind, and ſoul is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in it: and ſo being in one there is no idolatry, nor likeneſſes, but in one is the command, and power, &amp; life and will, and way, and worſhip; but all you who have taken on the Saints practice to performe the like, but not called, commanded, and furniſhed in Spirit, you want power and life, and ſo even in the time of your worſhip your hearts are going out after carnall things, and there is the ſpirituall idolatry: for what ever your minds are in, that is your God you wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and the pure God ownes no ſuch; for its truth in the inward parts he ſeeks for; wherein none of you can worſhip, who knowes not the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing word in your hearts, to keepe them up to God in your worſhip, and that worſhip which is not in the will of God is the worſhipping of Devills.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Error, Hereſie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is not Error to forſake the opinions of any man whatſoever, nor to with draw from the Church of Rome, as they call it; nor from any who have reformed ſome things ſince the time of popery, but yet are not come to the true foundation of the Apoſtles, though they call themſelves Nationall Churches, or Gathered Churches whatſoever. But the Error is to erre from the Spirit of God and its teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and that Church which by its teaching alone is gathered into God, out of all the wayes, worſhips, ſects, and opinions of the world, Convocations and Councels, that are not in God. And the Church ſo gathered into God is the pillar, and ground of truth; where the Spirit alone is teacher: and all that are gone out from this church, and Teaching, are in the Error, where all the Sects, and Opinions, and falſe wayes and worſhips are, and their teachers, who have erred<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from the Spirit of Chriſt, and the Saints teacher and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r practice, and are gone after their pride, &amp; covetuou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſs, and filthy lucre: here lyes the Worlds Teachers, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gh they do not know from whence th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y are Erred, becauſe they never yet came in the right way, nay who never yet came ſo far as <hi>Balaam,</hi> who had the word of the Lord from his ownmouth &amp; knew it, &amp; yet h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s heart erred after gifts and honour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So theſe pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch againſt <hi>Balaam,</hi> but cannot ſee themſelves in the ſame Error, ever ſince they were promoted to honour, and gifts, and Maiſterſhips, and great
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118947:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:118947:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118947:14"/>
Livings, by the pope, who received his power from the Beaſt, and gave of it to all his Adherents, to cauſe all that dwell on the earth to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip them, but ſuch whoſe names are written in the book of life, who have ſuffered to this day, and do ſuffer, becauſe they cannot bow to that power, nor worſhip it, nor according to its likneſs: and under pretence of Herefie and Eerror do theſe alwayes ſuffer, by ſuch who are Erred, and with the Spirit of Error do Judge; which Spirit hath ſhed all the innocent blood ſince <hi>Abel</hi> to this day, though the Error was ever in the perſecuter.</p>
               <p>So that there is no Error but who goes from the ſpirit of Chriſt and his teachings; and all who are gone from that, are into Error what ever they pretend. And that which leads from that Spirit, is the mother<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Confuſion, and vain Janglings, and Contention, diſpute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about the things of God, but are gone out into the world, where all the deceived ones are AntiChriſts, and ſeducing Spirits, which deceives the nations with inchantments and witcheries, which none can ſee till to the light of Chriſt, and his Spirit they return, which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leads out of all Errors, as it is beleived and followed. For no Spirit can lead out of Errors but that Spirit which never erred: and who ever is lead out by any other is Erred already, though unknown, to them who are ſo deceived. For Error could never Judge of Error, nor darkneſs of light, though it will be doing, to ſhew enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>So Error Cryes, Take heed of being deceived, which is deceived already; but the Spirit of light ſearcheth out that deceipt: but who walks not in the ſpirit and light of Chriſt, is blind, and knows not by what he is lead, nor whither; and ſtumbles at the light which ſhould Judge his blindneſs, and become his Leader, and ſuch a one though he be in Error, yet knows not whence he is fallen; who never knew the right way; as many at this day, who are talking of blindnes but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the pitt, and muſt be till they own the light to lead them out of it, which never Erred, which is of God, even as they who received it, are of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and they that were of God, knew, that all that would not heare them had the Spirit of Error; and thereby they knew it and the Spirit of truth.</p>
               <p>And what ever that be which leads out into the Worlds Conformity, and pleads for it, or any thing that is come in by the Fall, that is the Spirit of Error. But that Spirit which teſtifies againſt all that is in the fall, and convinceth of it, and leads out of it, thats the Spirit of truth, &amp; comes to teſtifie of the redeemer Chriſt Jeſus, who is to ſet free out of it, which all that lives in, lives in Error.</p>
               <p>So all who deſire to know the Spirit of Error, you muſt turn to the Spirit of light, from whence you have Erred: for no other thing ſhews the Error but that which reproves the fruit of Error, that which reproves for ſin, is that from which man hath Erred, the faithfull and true witneſs which is in the beginning of the Creation of God, to which all muſt give an account, and which alone is appointed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118947:14"/>
light, and leader of the people that ſit in darkneſs, to ſhew the darkneſs and the way out of it. So, to that which was in the beginning all muſt come, that with the light from which man hath Erred, you may know the wayes of Error, and the way of truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Faith.</head>
               <p>HE that hath living faith which is in Chriſt, lives by it, and the life that he lives is above all the world, and the powers of darkneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the leaſt meaſure of that Faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s perfect, and is preſent power againſt all the aſſaults of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acan, if in it the Creature abide faithfull, and run not to other helps, and ſo lay himſelf open to diſtruſt; for it is the gift of God, whereof whoſoever receives a meaſure, he hath a meaſure of the Son, above which he Father will not ſuffer any temptation: for the true faith laies hold upon Gods righteouſneſſe, againſt which no unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe can prevaile; which righteouſneſſe is received by faith in Chriſt Jeſus; wherein the Creature ſo believing ſtands armed againſt all the fierie darts, and temptations of the Devill, with Gods righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, ſeene in the light, and wrought in the Spirit; whereby the Creature becomes Gods workmanſhip, created in Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Jeſus unto good works, by which he becomes free from the evill; dead to ſin, but alive to Gods righteouſneſſe, waiting in faith, to ſee it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed through obedience thereto, from faith to faith; and it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, The juſt ſhall live by faith; and this is the living faith, which pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifies the heart, unto the life of godlineſſe; and ſo reveales the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of faith for an inheritance, everlaſting righteouſneſſe, ever growing and ſpringing, whereby the Creature grows into the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, with him to walke, by faith, out of the knowledge of all the world, tranſlated out of the pleaſures and kingdoms of it, into the kingdom of the Son of God, where the reproach of Chriſt is eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed great riches, laying hold upon the inviſible, which the worlds faith cannot reach, which caryes them no higher then viſible reaſonings, and conſulting with ſenſuall wiſdom, and carnall helps, and ſo brings nothing to perfection, becauſe it ſees nothing that is perfect; but the liying faith ſees him that is inviſible; and layes hold on the meaſure of God made manifeſt in Spirit, which meaſure of the Spirit is that which in the faith worketh out the old, and worketh the new, both will and deed, whoſe worke is perfect, to kill and make alive.</p>
               <p>But the worlds faith is not of this nature and power, who heare a thing with the outward care, and ſo ſet themſelves to believe, or not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118947:15"/>
believe it; in their wills or outward perſwaſion, from others, or in their own imagination, and as their imaginations thoughts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivings, changes; ſo their faith changes alſo, and ſo it cannot be ſteadfaſt, becauſe it ſtands not in the meaſure of God known in the heart which changes not: and this faith ſerves not God nor can it pleaſe him, nor doth it ſee him that is inviſible. And ſo not ſtanding in that which is contrary to the will of man, and power of ſin, it lies under the wills of men, and power of the Prince of this world; and as the world and times changes ſo doth that faith, but can never lead out of the world, and all time, up to the redeemer of the ſoul. And to all who are in that nature, the living faith that ſtands in that which is of God in a pure conſcience is a myſtery, not known nor received, and ſo cannot be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved; which is the true faith, which is the gift of God, which none<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 9.</note> can receive but in the Spirit. So the faith of Chriſt and the faith of the world are two, and have their ſeverall effects, and fruits; the one profeſſeth freedome and redemption, in the imaginations and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, but is a ſervant of ſin; the other hath the living faith which gives the life of freedom, and ſo as is their ground and roote, ſo is their fruits and effects; and the one of theſe is againſt the other. For that<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 27.</note> faith which ſtands in Chriſt, believes in purity, and perfection, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſſe, and ſlays ſin, and by that faith alone the juſt lives<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and juſtice and righteouſneſſe is brought forth to light, in the godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation: but that faith which ſtands in the imaginations and wiſdom of man, which believes ſalvation without holyneſſe of life, that ſlaies the juſt, and keeps alive the unjuſt; and this faith they had which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the Scriptures, and the words of the Prophets, and that God was their Father; but not having the word of Faith in their hearts theſe ſlew the Son of God, and ſet the murtherer free: and as that faith, which is dead, works death; ſo that faith which is living worketh life. And a profeſſion of faith without righteouſneſſe, is like a body without life: and like as a living man is known by his actions, ſo is the living faith by its fruits. And as the man cannot live without action, no more<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jeames</hi> 2. 18.</note> can faith in Chriſt without righteouſneſſe; theſe are inſeparable,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10, 6. 10.</note> therefore its called the righteouſneſſe of faith; where the heart believes unto righteouſneſſe, there the mouth confeſſeth to ſalvation, without hypocriſie of ſelfe righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>And ſo Gods righteouſneſſe is received in the heart by faith, and by obedience thereto brought forth into the world, a witneſſe againſt all the unrighteouſneſſe of the world: and ſo the righteouſneſſe of God is preached through faith, in all, whoſe faith ſtands in Chriſt Jeſus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but that is a dead faith which brings not forth the life of Chriſt into the<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 10. 21.</note> world; and thats the reprobate faith which is to the good worke repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate: and he that errs from the righteouſneſſe, errs from the faith al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, which is held in a pure conſcience: and he that makes ſhipwrack of a good conſcience, and puts that away, makes ſhipwrack of faith alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:118947:15"/>And in the eternall light is all your faith ſeene and judged to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt and without foundation, who are out of the light, and out of the life. And your Faith is ſeen to be the ſame with the Scribes and Phariſees, who believed the Scriptures, and thought to find life therein; but did not believe in the Light, and ſo would not come to Chriſt, that they might have life. So all your Faith, which is out of the Light, which from the Letter you have formed, is a Faith ſet up in your own Wills, and not that which is given of God: For that Faith that is the gift of God, believes in the Light, and follows it, and ſo leads to the Life; and this Faith that ſtands in the Light, and Life, is the living Faith, and never without Works; which Works are Love, Meekneſſe, Patience, Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Sanctification, Juſtification, &amp;c. the Works of God in Chriſt Jeſus, in which Gods Workmanſhip is ſeen in the new Creation, received in the Faith, and in the obedience to which the Soul is purified, and Victory witneſſed over the World, Sinne, and Death. But you who believe not in the Light, are Enemies to this Faith, and yet you get the Words of the Scripture given forth from the Light; and ſo your Faith ſtands in the Wiſdome of words, into which you have been ſearching with your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but not in the power of God and his Work: ſo you are they who ſay, and do not, whoſe practice could never ſuit your Profeſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Hope.</head>
               <p>HOpe is a gift of God and is pure, and ſtands in that which is pure ſhewing that purity of God and his righteouſneſs<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 8.</note> in Chriſt Jeſus, the beholding whereof ſtayes the ſoul<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 4, 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> from Joyning to the wicked one, when he tempteth; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe<note place="margin">2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> he ſees in the light a better worke to ſerve: ſo that untill the time of that work being manifeſt, the hope is as an Anchor to ſtay from following the unclean one, and ſo keeps out of the ſin, and ſo makes not aſhamed, even in the time of want: it hopes againſt<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> hope. When that life of Chriſt is not yet ſeen in its full power yet it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced in the hope which is wrought in the patience &amp; experience,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 12, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> whereby the love appeares and the faith workes, whereby Gods righteouſnes is revealed, and the Son is ſeen, who is the redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and he that hath this hope in him, purifies himſelf even as he is pure. And this is that hope that enters within the vail into the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place, where the life and immortality is brought to light, which the mortall eye nor carnall ſenſes cannot approach to; and this is the <hi>living hope,</hi> which hopes to the end: <hi>That Chriſt, and his righteouſneſs may be revealed, to take away ſin, and ſave from it, and out of it; and in hope of this the Children and babes of Chriſt wait in the obedience of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118947:16"/>
the Spirit, not faſhioning themſelves after the luſts of ignorance, but as he who hath called to that hope is holy, ſo in his holineſs is their converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who are in his hope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Devill hath begotten an other hope as like this as may be in his ſervants, who beleive him, and are acted by his Spirit; which ſtands in an other ground, and brings forth an other fruit: And that is, <hi>That though they be ſervants to ſin</hi> (for that muſt be Concluded in all his Covenants and graces) yet there is hopes of ſalvation; and ſuch hopes as may not be Judged falſe, nor queſtioned; although the witneſs of God in the conſcience doth teſtifie to the contrary, yet it muſt not be heeded, leſt they be deluded; <hi>So that where he is become teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 12</note> 
                  <hi>a tender conſcience, to is be reſiſted as the greateſt Error, and foolery in the world; and that, To wait for the teſtimony or witneſs within, is to deny Chriſt at Jeruſalem, and the greateſt blaſphemy that can be ſpoken of; and to wait for that myſtery that hath been hid from ages, (to wit) Chriſt</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>within, the hope of glory, is to deny the perſon of Chriſt, and his blood and ſufferings.</hi> And many ſuch imaginations hath he begott in peoples brains, to ſcare them from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inding the light of Chriſt within, <hi>that ſo he may</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4. 18. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>keep the heart in darkneſs, and his ſeat there undiſcovered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So he ſets them to look for the kingdom of Chriſt without them, and a ſpirit without, and a light without, and a word without, and righteouſneſs without, and in that to hope, while he dwells in the heart, and there, in darkneſs</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 17. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>upholds his kingdom of ſin, and ſeat of unrighteouſneſs, all their life, and feeds them with a hope after they be dead, by a profeſſion without power,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>and life, and ſpirit, and truth in them, to order them, and their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6,</note> 
                  <hi>a right, towards God and man, in their generation:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 11.</note> and this is the hope of the hypocrite, that muſt periſh, in the end, and come ſhort of ſalvation, <hi>whoſe hope is not in God, nor gives being</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 8</note> 
                  <hi>in his righteouſneſs,</hi> but he hath a hope, and lives in the world without<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 21.</note> God, and his hope: And this is not the hope of Chriſt, which lives in ſin, and hopes for ſalvation; but this is his hope, that hopes to free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 17.</note> and perfection, which never comes ſhort of its end, in all that<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 17. 8.</note> wait in it; and this hope only is it that maketh not aſhamed. But you<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 7. 17.</note> may be aſhamed of your hope, who are found in your ſins, and<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hab.</hi> 7. 19.</note> encouraging your ſelves therein, that you ſhall not dye.</p>
               <p>That's the Devils hope, which hopes not freedome from ſinne, as much as freedome from Hell. And with this hope would he make God a Lyar, and partial, like himſelf, that he ſhould find ſome in ſinne, and ſave them; and others in ſinne, and condemn them. But who knows Chriſt, and hopes in him, hopes in righteouſneſſe, and therein to ſtand in the day of Judgment, and therein to live in this evil world above it, and all the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe of it. And the end of the lively hope, is no leſſe, then Gods righteouſneſſe to attain, and live in, as it is received; and onely<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 14, 15.</note> ſuch can give a Reaſon of the Hope that is in them, <hi>Who ſanctifie the Lord God in their hearts, and have a good conſcience, and ſuffer for well-doing;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 8. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>which unreaſonable men, who live in the unreaſonable nature, cannot do, whoſe Hope is not an Helmet of Salvation againſt Sinne, yet would have it for Salvation againſt Hell.</hi> And this is the unreaſonable Hope, in unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118947:16"/>
men, for which they can give no reaſon, but in their own Wills and Imaginations; for is there any reaſon why you ſhould hope to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Chriſt, who will be the Devils ſervants, to yield your members ſervants to, and delight in his wickedneſſe while you live, and yet be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Chriſts righteouſneſſe when you die? This is a Hope that ſerves you to talk on, to feed your ſelves in your vanities; but will be in the end like the giving up of the Ghoſt. But who is begotten into the lively Hope are begotten into an Inheritance, uncorruptible and undefiled, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they are kept by the power in Hope, through Faith, unto Salvation from ſinne, the thing that he thats begotten of God, longs and hopes for; which Hope ſhall not faile.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Love.</head>
               <p>THe love of God is but one, and in One; nor can any receive it, but who receives that one, the Son of God; and this cannot ſtand with Self, or any changable thing; for God is that love, and none can dwell in it, but as he dwels in God: ſo it's pure and perfect. As the Creature comes to live in God as he is, into his Image and likeneſſe; ſo with the pure Light his love is ſeen, and ſhed abroad in the heart, whereby the power of Faith worketh to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming all that is contrary to God: ſo the love of God abounds, and who dwels in it, worketh none ill; but the Work of Love fulfills the Law of God, which is upon all that's gone out from him, into the world, &amp; ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends, which hath received-in the love of carnal things, and ſo are gone into the enmity againſt God, ſetting the Affection on changable things: for whoſoever will be a friend to the worlds is the enemy of God; for the Worlds love ariſes from the Spirit of the World, but the love of God is a fruit of Gods Spirit, and none hath the love of God, but who hath that Spirit from which it ſprings, which is Eternal, Unchangeable, and above all Carnal things: nor can Time, or Carnal things, quench it, for it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures for ever, and herein it differs from all the worlds love: nor can any one have this love, but in the Fountain of love, even the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods love ſhed in the heart, wherewith he firſt loved the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and this being known and ſeen in the Light, from thence is the Spring of Love, which runs out to the whole Creation of God, and for the ſame end: for as the love is one, ſo the End is but one.</p>
               <p>Now God ſo loved the World, that he gave his Son into the World, a Light to condemn ſin in the fleſh, that the righteouſneſſe of God might be fulfilled in the Creature, in walking after the Spirit, and denying the Works of the fleſh: and this is the love of God to ſinners, to condemn ſinne, and take it away in the Light, and life of Chriſt, and to all that love
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118947:17"/>
with this love: this is the end of it: But with this love is all your love condemned, whoſe love ſtands in Faſhions and Cuſtomes, Feaſtings, and Ryotings, Sports and vain Pleaſures, or any thing in the fleſh; that's in the Fall, and in flattering one another in your evil wayes, or in reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or any other thing that hath an end; for the love of God is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end, in love to the Soul and Body, as God hath made it, but in hatred to all that is come in ſince, which hath defiled it.</p>
               <p>So that this love of God conſiſts of Reproofs, Judgment, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, againſt all that defiles the Creation, and againſt the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture who yields to that pollution; and this is pure love to the Soul, that deals faithfully therewith, in declaring its condition; and that was the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.</note> great love Chriſt ſhewed the Jews, when he told them they were Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, blind guids, Lyars; and ſaid, <hi>Wo unto you, ye Serpents, ye Generation of Vipers, how can ye eſcape the damnation of hell?</hi> And many ſuch plain true<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 10</note> words he ſpoke in love to them. And that was the love of God in <hi>Paul,</hi> which ſaid to <hi>Elimas. O full of all ſubtilty, and all miſchief, thou Child of the Devil, thou enemy of all righteouſneſſe, wilt thou not ceaſe to pervent the right wayes of the Lord?</hi> For all the love that can be ſhewed to any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is to deal faithfully and truly with them, as they are ſeen in the Light; and he who doth not ſo, loves neither God nor them, (as will be found in the day of Judgment) and ſo are out of <hi>Gods</hi> love, and have imagined a love which is of another nature: and with this love, ſuch as are out of the love of <hi>God,</hi> flatter one another in your <hi>evil wayes,</hi> and <hi>changable opinions;</hi> which love is grounded in <hi>carnal things,</hi> and ſtands in your own <hi>Wills.</hi> And therewith, when you will, you love; and when you will, you hate; (but neither knows love, nor hatred, as it is in <hi>God</hi>)<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1. 9, 6.</note> whoſe love and hatred ſtands in <hi>changeable things;</hi> ſo your love and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred periſheth, which ſtands not in <hi>God.</hi> But who knows the love of <hi>God,</hi> tramples upon all your love and hatred, and ſees an end thereof. And ſuch ſees your blindneſſe, who ſay you would have all wone by love, but know not whereof you affirm, whoſe wayes is not Gods ways, nor your<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2. 27.</note> thoughts, his; <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I will redeem Zion with Judgment; and with</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>the Spirit of Judgment, and burning, will I waſh away the filth thereof:</hi> But You who are in your filth, would have all flattered therein.</p>
               <p>So, that love is ſeen to be filthy, which ſpares filthineſſe, which defiles the Temple of God; but that is pure, which purges away the filth, and condemns the Unclean, and all that loves it: For the love of the Devil may be wone with ſerving of him, and flattering him in his wayes, in them in whom he is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But what is it worth? So may one have the love of all the World, and their friendſhip; but woe unto that friendſhip, which is got by ſparing Gods enemies; that, is enmity againſt God: <hi>Therefore,</hi> faith<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 4.</note> God, <hi>let love be without diſſimulation, abhor that which is evill, cleave to</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>that which is good;</hi> and that love is it, which covers ſinne, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns ſin unto death, and covers it with righteouſneſſe: <hi>Otherwiſe,</hi> ſaith the Scriptures, <hi>he that covereth ſinne, ſhal not proſper:</hi> And, ſaith <hi>James,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 28. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Jam. 5. 20. He which converteth a ſinner from the error of his way ſhall ſave a</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 29. 5.</note>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118947:17"/>
                  <hi>ſoul, and ſhall hide a multitude of ſinnes;</hi> And, ſaith <hi>Solomon; Open rebuke, is better th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t love:</hi> ſuch wounds are precious, to them that know what love is; but he that ſpares mens wickedneſſe, hates Gods righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. And ſo with the Light is ſeen, Gods love, and the Devils love; and each loves his own works, and ſo do their Children in whom they raign: For who ever loves the one, hates the other; and he that ſerves the one, hates the other; and ſo the Servant pleads for his Maſter, whom he loves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Judgment.</head>
               <p>TRue Judgment (as it is known to men) is a gift from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, ſet in the heart of every one who dwells in the Light of Chriſt, which Judgmennt paſſeth upon all that's in the Creature, contrary to the life of God, and ſo, as it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, ſprings up with Light and Salvation, to the redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the heart from all uncleanneſſe, condemning all which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to purity, that God may be ſeen in his dwelling place with his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe; and ſo he is ſaid to redeem Zion with Judgment, and her<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 27<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> Converts with Righteouſneſſe, and to purge away the filth of the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Zion with the Spirit of Judgment, and the Spirit of burning. And if there be a dwelling in the Light, this Judgment ceaſes not, till the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4. 4.</note> Throne of Chriſt be eſtabliſhed in the heart in peace; for this is his Judgment, and is upon all that ſtands up againſt his Kingdom; and this<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 7.</note> is the cauſe why the enemies of righteouſneſſe love it not, but have tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it into gall and wormwood; which the righteous delights in, and loves, who are redeemed and ſaved therewith, and knows it to be the the Promiſe firſt to be received: <hi>For,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will make Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>to reſt for a light of the people;</hi> which being received, his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is neer to be revealed.</p>
               <p>Therefore, his Judgment muſt paſſe before, upon all that's Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and none can have his righteouſneſſe, but who receives his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Therefore,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>I have hewed them by the Prophets, I have ſlain them by the words of my mouth, and my Judgments are as a Light that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>goeth forth;</hi> And for this end, is Judgment given to the Saints of the moſt High. <hi>And,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>righteous men ſhall judge them after the manner of Adultereſſes, and after the manner of women that ſhed blood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are Adultereſſes, and blood is in their hands, thus will I cauſe loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ceaſe out of the Laud.</hi> Therefore is <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſo often commanded to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118947:18"/>
judge them, and cauſe them to know their abominations. And <hi>Jeremy</hi> was full of the fury of the Lord, and he was weary with hold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in. And <hi>Micah</hi> was full of power by the Spirit of the Lord, and of Judgment, to declare to <hi>Jacob</hi> his tranſgreſſion, and to <hi>Iſrael</hi> his ſinne. And ſo in all<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 6. 11.</note> Ages he placed his Judgments in his ſervants, who were to judge the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and ſuch as knew not God, therewith; and ſo many as did believe<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mic.</hi> 3. 8.</note> it, and receive it, did repent and found mercy, and the reſt were hardened. And this judgment is eternal, and ſhall ſtand in Heaven, as it is paſſed upon earth. And this was committed to the Apoſtles as a Doctrine; and<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 2.</note> whom they bound, were bound; and who by it they looſed, were looſed: therefore did all the Saints love judgment: for it is the miniſtration of Chriſt miniſtred out upon all that's againſt Chriſt, and that which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt, is againſt the Soul: ſo this judgment muſt begin at the<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 17</note> houſe of God: but where the Devil keeps the houſe, he rejects it; and, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> the ungodly ſcorneth Judgment, and evill men underſtand it not. So, ſaith he, there i that's deſtroyed for want of Judgment; and<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 19. 28.</note> he that hath not Judgment is blind, and ſees not that his Enemy raigns, which muſt raign till Judgment be brought into victory, and ſet in the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.</note> earth; but when Judgment is laid to the Line, and Righteouſneſſe to the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 13. 25.</note> Plummet, then the Covenant with Hell and Death muſt be diſanulled: ſo all that are in this Covenant loves not that which breaks it.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28. 17, 18.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And this is your Caſe, who hates reproof, who when you are told of your evil hearts where ſinne lives, and your curſed crooked natures, you ſay, <hi>Who made thee a Judge?</hi> And many ſay, You could like what we ſay, but that we judge people: ſo you are they that hate Judgment, and would not have the Miniſtry of Chriſt to go on; for who hath the Spirit of Chriſt, hath the Spirit of Judgment; and who ſerves that Spirit, muſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffer it to ſpeak, and judge in them; and all that oppoſe it, ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by it: <hi>Therefore,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, the tongue of the Righteous talketh judgment, the Law of God is in his heart, his ſteps ſhall not ſlide, but the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137. 30, 31, 32.</note> 
                  <hi>ſeekech to ſlay him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>So for uttering the Judgments of God againſt the Wicked, have the juſt ever ſuffered; and for the ſame, do you now hate them, and condemn them, and you are in the ſame nature and covenant that your Fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers was in, who ſhed the innocent bloud; and you would have joyned with them, had you lived with them, what ever your deceipt may ſay to the contrary. And you are found in the ſame Oppoſition to the utmoſt power you have againſt the Spirit of Judgment now, as they was then; and the cauſe is the ſame now, as it was then, both they and you living in that which is for Judgment, Fire, and Condemnation: therefore you cannot receive their Teſtimony, who have that evil judged and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which you love and live in; and for this cauſe, <hi>Cain</hi> ſlew his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo do all his generation; and with that which you hate, ſhall you be condemned, and ſhall not be able to ſtand in judgment, which is the Saints delight, in which they are united to God, as he hath ſaid, <hi>I</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oſ.</hi> 2. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>will betroth ye unto me for ever in righteouſneſs and in judgment:</hi> which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118947:18"/>
righteouſnes and Judgment muſt condemn the wicked. So who hath Chriſt hath him in Judgment and righteouſneſs, and loves him, his Judgment, and righteouſneſs; but who is married unto the world cannot love that which is his Condemnation, for ſo doing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Perfection.</head>
               <p>GOd is perfect, and ſo is all his works, and all his gifts; and who ever receives his gifts receives that which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. And by receiving and joyning to that which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is the creature made perfect. And no farther then the creature is in this perfection, can any be united to God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor appeare in his ſight, nor be bleſſed, but is gone out into the curſe, from what was in the beginning, and ſo is in the fall, unredeemed, and hath no more of Chriſt, then what he hath of perfection: for perfection is of Chriſt, and imperfection is of the Devill; and theſe are two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traryes, and comes from contrary grounds, and brings forth contrary fruits; for he that is of God is of perfection, and believes perfection, but who is of the Serpent cannot own it, nor beleive it, being blinded by the God of this world. So God ſent his ſon into the world to preach perfection, even the perfection of the Father; that all who will believe may inherit it; and all that believed him believed perfection: And when he had left a perfect example, in all things, he aſcended and gave gifts to men, ſeveral ſorts of gifts; all for the perfecting the Saints that all might come up to one faith to a perfect man, to the meaſure, and ſtature, and fulneſs of Chriſt: that ſo he may be an everlaſting redeemer perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the work of God in every generation, of them that believe in his work and follow him. And this all his miniſters improved to the ſame end, and preached and prayed that they might preſent every man perfect in Chriſt Jeſus from whom they had received the gift, and all that believed them believed perfection, and preſſed after it as the end of their faith, knowing nothing leſe then perfection could give them reſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <p>Now ſince the miſtery of iniquity entred, there is another miniſtry gone out into the world who hath taken up an imitation inſtead of gift, &amp; have begotten an other kind of faith in the world, wholly reprobate as to perfection, preaching againſt it with all the power that may be, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it for blaſphemy, and calling it a doctrine of Devills and the like. And theſe would be called, the miniſters of Chriſt, that ſo they may not miſſe of their end: for did they come in his name whoſe work they up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, he knows they might run in vain. Thus they deceive all, who receive them, by their words; but who mindes the end of their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118947:19"/>
work, may eaſily ſee as much difference as is betwixt Chriſt and <hi>Belial,</hi> the work of Chriſt is and ever was to renew man again to his perfect eſtate, but the work of Antichriſt is to withſtand it, and each hath his miniſters ſutable to their ends intended: Chriſts end is to perfect, the devils is to keep unperfect. And each miniſters have their faith, hope, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gifts, ſutable; one pure, the other polluted: and according to each faith, ſo it is, to all that believe them, &amp; follow them; for the faith of Chriſt is a ſhield, &amp; gives victory over uncleanneſs ſin and evill, but the devills faith lets in, and believes it muſt be ſo; for, had not the devil firſt brought man to beleive him, rather then God, he could not have polluted what God had perfected. And the ſame way he takes to keep up his work by which at firſt he wrought it.</p>
               <p>So none can come to know a new creature but who can believe perfection; nor can any come to God, nor Chriſt, nor Gods righteouſneſs, but who comes to perfection. For all who are in the unperfect righteouſneſs are in your own righteouſneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the leſt meaſure of Gods righteouſneſs, is perfect: and all are in, perfection who become ſervants to it, and thereby become free from ſin: So by your unbeliefe you deſtroy your ſouls who are in your own works, which makes nothing perfect: &amp; ſo, meaſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſelves with your ſelves, cuts you off from Chriſt: as meaſureing your faith by your own ability, ſo ſtanding in that covenant which makes nothing perfect; but the coming in of a better hope doth: and this all know whoſe faith ſtands in what God is, and not what we can do; in everlaſting righteouſneſs, not in what we have to work; the one being righteouſneſs by faith revealed, a gift put into the believer; the other an Imitation of the ſame in works but not the power: and ſuch are you who read a verſe, and ſee therein what the Saints did, and then ſet your ſelves to do the like, but know not that righteouſnes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in you in the faith which they had, which was wrought in them, by the Lord, before they brought it to light, and ſo did not work, but beleived on him who worketh the will and the deed of his own good pleaſure, who alone is well pleaſed with his own work, and with all who are ſervants to his work, to bring it to light, to his praiſe, whoſe work-manſhip ſuch are. And they who are found herein, have his witneſs in the light, to prove their workes that they are wrought in God, and not of ſelf, ſelf-will, nor for ſelf-ends nor in ſelf-time, nor in ſelf-power and all that know this perfect will and acceptable worke of God knows it begotten and brought forth in ſelf deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, in all things, and not of us, but of him that is perfect; and ſo makes our way perfect. And this is the covenant that makes perfect all that comes thereto: and ſelf being denied in the work, boaſting is excluded, by the law of faith, which receives the free and perfect gift.</p>
               <p>And for this cauſe the firſt covenant was found faulty and diſanulled, becauſe it made not the commers thereto perfect as pertaining to the conſcience; nor did exclude boaſting: no more doth your imitations from the letter: for the light in your conſciences witneſs your imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, therein; and your works is condemned before they be wrought:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118947:19"/>
and your miniſters tells you your righteouſneſs is not perfect, yet they call for righteouſneſs, and yet ſay, your beſt is but as filthy raggs: and they call for prayer, and yet tell you that you muſt be wicked while you live, and that the prayers of the wicked are abomination to the Lord. So the abominable ſacrifice is preached, and performed; and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on denied by all thoſe prieſts and people who have not received the gift for perfecting. And of this ſort are they who have their preaching to ſtudy and to ſeek at other mens mouthes, or from the Letter; but have it not from the mouth of the Lord, freely given, the perfect gift, for perfecting the Saints: ſo, what they get that they ſell, for none can give freely but who ſo receives, nor can any, perfect others, who have not the perfect gift themſelves.</p>
               <p>So you that talk of perfection, you muſt firſt know, a free gift from above. Perfection is not from below, where you have your carnal ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and reaſon, and wiſdom, and prudence, gotten by your learning and ſtudies, whereof you boaſt, and wherein you exalt your ſelves above your brethren: for that came in by the devil, and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is hid from it, and all that live therein; nither can it be bought or ſold nor procured with all the induſtry of man Only ſuch obtain it who wait in the light, till they receive the free gift of rigteouſneſs, and be indued with power from above; Not they who heare a thing in the notion and then declare it; nor who ſee a work done, and go do the like; for none was more like to have been able miniſters then the Apoſtles in this, who had ſeen the mighty works of Chriſt and heard him and his doctrine; but theſe were not fit for perfecting the Saints till they had received the ſame Spirit from above; Therefore was they commanded to wait at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> till therewith they was indued; and then they was made able mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, not of the letter: but of the ſpirit; and their teſtament in the ſpirit, &amp; not old in the letter, for that of the letter kills, but the Spirit perfects.</p>
               <p>And ſo all that ever beare the teſtament in ſpirit preach and beleive perfection, but that teſtimony of the letter being without, cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the comers thereto: for the light, faith, hope, love, patience &amp;c. are gifts Spiritually given for perfecting, and cannot be had any other way but in ſpirit, freely given and freely received, which gifts you know not, nor the effect of them, who are in the literal miniſtration; but in your vain imaginations and comprehenſions, are Judging you know not what. And limitting the ſpirituall covenant of God to the literall, and becauſe you who are in the letter (ſearching with your witt) can find no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, therefore you will judge the ſpirituall covenant alſo: That ſo the devill may for ever keep people from the coming in of the better hope: for if the firſt covenant made nothing perfect, nor the ſecond neither, what hope is there for people; ſeeing no imperfection can enter into the kingdom of heaven?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:118947:20"/>
               <head>Concerning Government, or Magiſtracy.</head>
               <p>THere is no juſt government, but what is of God, and in whomſoever he (having called them) placeth his power, and authority; which is juſt, and righteous, received in the light, and from the anointing of Jeſus, and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to his ſpiritual power in the ſoul, whom the Father hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed King and Governour of all things in heaven and in earth: And none can deſerve the name of Chriſtian governors, but who by him are governed, and do receive his authority, with ſubjection there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto in Spirit. Therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher power. And he that will rule for God, muſt firſt ſee that his own ſoul be ſubject to the higher power, &amp; muſt know one higher then hee: and ſo himſelfe, coming under that power, then with that power &amp; authority upon him he goes forth to rule with God, for God; and having ſet up his Kingdom in his heart, he goes to make way that his Kingdom may be ſet up in others; that all may bow to his authority wherewith he is anointed from above; and to which he is become ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject for conſcience ſake. And ſo his government, being according to that in every conſcience, every one that minds that in the conſcience ſhall witneſſe him and his government to be of God, and ſo he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts ſhall receive to himſelfe damnation, witneſſed by that in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: and all who own not that in the conſcience which is pure, to obey the Lord therein, the ſword of the Lord in the hand of his Miniſter ſhall be upon ſuch; and that of God to which he is ſubject, even the anointing he hath received ſhall inſtruct him in the Spirit of meekeneſſe wiſdome, and judgment to find out the tranſgreſſor, and lay the ſword upon him: and ſuch ſhall not beare the ſword in vaine; but a terror to the evil doer ſhall be, without reſpect to the perſons of men, or any other thing, but onely to the law of God; which is one with that in the conſcience,</p>
               <p>So is Chriſt honoured as Lawgiver, and Judge, and King; and with this honour he honoureth ſuch Rulers in the conſciences of all his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and before all the world, and though the world knows not the authority of ſuch, nor from whom they have it; yet all that feare God doe; and are made to confeſſe them before God and man, and ſo <hi>Iſay</hi> was made to confeſſe to <hi>Cyrus,</hi> whom others counted a Heathen; for it is the authority in the perſon that is honourable, where ever it is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118947:20"/>
ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> was dreadfull in this authority, though otherwiſe but a ſhepheard, and the meekeſt man in the world: and <hi>Samuel</hi> a poore man, yet this authority made the Elders of <hi>Bethlem</hi> to tremble at his coming when they heard thereof. Nay it is too much to inſtance in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; for all that ever honoured God in this, he honoured them, whoſe names are a bleſſing to this day, and their memoriall ſhall not rott; for when ſuch raignes the people rejoyce, that delights in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, the juſt are bold, and righteouſneſſe flouriſhes in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſtreets; and wickedneſſe is aſhamed and is hid, and the innocent clap their hands for joy that the Lord raignes, and their governors are of themſelves. When Chriſt rules all in all, then he makes his Officers peace and his exactors righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>But if it be ſaid, Muſt not men own wicked Majeſtrates? I ſay they are to be owned and obeyed in all things, as they are appointed by God, for God limits them, and hath ſet bounds to them, though they know it not, and ſo far as they command the will of God, they are to be obeyed for conſcience ſake, but when they are contrary to God, and command that which God forbids, and forbid what he commands, then God is to be obeyed and man denyed for Conſcienceſake, for none can be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for conſcience ſake, who commands that which is contrary to that of God in the conſcience; though many do deny the Lord, and conforme to ſuch; yet who are guided by the Spirit of God, which keeps the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience cleane, never could; but in all ages have ſuffered violence from ſuch to keepe their conſciences void of offence; for ſo it muſt be when rulers themſelves deny obedience to God in Spirit, then all who walk after the Spirit muſt needs ſuffer by them.</p>
               <p>And here is the ground of all perſecution that ever was, when gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors are out of the feare of God, and ſtand in their owne wills, and walke after the fleſh, then that ſeed rules, which perſecutes him that is borne after the Spirit, and ſo the enmity getting up, ſnares are laid for the innocent, to make him an offender for a word, who is none in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: And from this ground have the Lambes beene devoured always as evill doers, but ever innocent; yet never wanting accuſations, as Heretickes, Ring-leaders of Sects and Seditions, Blaſphemers, and the like; that ſo the Devill may the more blind the world, leaſt they ſhould ſee his envie and their innocency.</p>
               <p>And in the time of ſuch governors hath the Lambe borne teſtimony in much patience, meekeneſſe and long ſuffering, bearing all the venom and envie that the Serpent could caſt out upon him, (where he was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in the creature) for a witneſſe againſt all ſuch rulers; that his long ſuffering might lead them to repentance, and leave them without excuſe in the day of his wrath: and againſt ſuch is he finiſhing his teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony at this day: And a blinder generation never was in any age, who have run from all tenderneſſe, ſo far into that wiſdom, that many are grown wholly paſt feeling; impriſoning, whipping, and torturing their brethren for ſuch things, as never any age of perſecution can paralell
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118947:21"/>
And it muſt needs be ſo: for as every generation of that ſeed growes more ſubtill, ſo (to the things of Chriſt) more blind and deafe. So that its rare, to find one who hath an eare to heare oppreſſion; but not one, whoſe heart is perfect to deny the worlds favour; to beare witneſſe againſt the ground of oppreſſion: ſo the juſt man periſheth and none layes it to heart, nor can any lay it to heart whoſe hearts are filled with ſelfiſh paſſion, and ſelfe will; for none can rule for God, whoſe heart is not ruled by God, but when the Lord rules in the heart, then the juſt raignes, and the cauſe of the juſt is heard, and he that rules for the juſt rules for God, and with God, over the unjuſt; firſt in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, then in all the world; otherwiſe though an unjuſt Judge may heare the cauſe of the poore in ſome caſe, or time, yet it is not for God, nor from obedience to the Spirit of Judgment which is of God, the heart being filled with ſelf ends.</p>
               <p>So that he that is a ſelfe lover, or proud, or covetous, or reſpects gifts, or rewards, cannot rule for God: nor he that reſpects perſons cannot rule for God: nor with God, who is no reſpecter of perſons, but only hath reſpect to ſuch as walk in obedience to that juſt principle, of himſelf: nor ſuch as ſeeke for honour from men, cannot rule for God; for ſuch are out of the faith of Chriſt and in the unreaſonable nature, ſeeking the praiſe of men and ſo cannot have the praiſe of God; for the friendſhip of the world is enmity with God, and he that ſeeks the one loſes the other. And ſuch as are out of the feare of God cannot rule for God, for ſuch are ſubject to be drawne with feare or favour of men, from the juſt principle of God, out of which none can rule for God.</p>
               <p>And herein is the cleare difference betwixt Heathens and Chriſtians. The one exerciſe Juſtice, and Judgment, and righteouſneſſe, which is of God, and in his will, whereby they rule over all unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of men of corrupt minds, and principles whatſoever, and ſtand in the authority of God a terror to the evill doer: The other execiſe Lordſhip over mens perſons, in their own wills, which they ſet up in their ſelfiſh principle, in carnall pollicy, who lay the ſword upon the juſt as on the unjuſt, if he bow not to their wills: which who ſtands in the will of God may not do, and ſo they that abide in the feare of God, do ever ſuffer by ſuch as are out of his feare. And though theſe be ſet in their places by the permiſſion, or appointment of God, yet not knowing him, who ordereth all things, to order them; though they are reſtrained from evill, or made to do his will, yet have they no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, nor ſhare in it, not doing it in obedience to God, nor from a principle of equity, not knowing Chriſt guiding and leading them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; they are no Chriſtians, what-ever they may call themſelves.</p>
               <p>And to ſuch as theſe who mind not that of God to governe withall, hath God ſent his ſervants to teſtifie to their faces of their departure from the juſt principle, and ſo cannot pleaſe God with his government, (yet did they never plot againſt them, nor murmur) which if they did heare, they rejoyced to ſee them eſtabliſhed as a bleſſing to the place and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118947:21"/>
which the people of God ever ſeeke to God for; but if they heare not, then they are made to mourne that God ſhould be grieved and his Creature loſt, eſpecially in ſuch a place by which God may be ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured, and a Nation or Towne plagued from the Lord for his ſake, who hath the ſword of God in his hand and ſuffers ſin, but puniſhes the innocent, both which the Lord will revenge, and ſeldom but the place where it is done taſtes thereof, which ſuch as rule with God, and for him, prevent: yea by ſuch the peace hath beene lengthned after the Judgment hath beene pronounced. So when the righteous raignes, God is honoured and good men rejoyce; but when wickedneſſe gets up in the King, then the Lord is diſhonoured, and the glory departs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Obedience.</head>
               <p>SPiritual and living obedience, is not that of mans way and will wherein men and women (in the firſtbirth, and wiſdom therein) read the Scriptures, and there find what the Saints performed in the Spirit and power of the Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and from that ſet themſelves on work to do the like; and ſo make an imitation inſtead of obedience, and ſet up ſelfe, works inſtead of Chriſts works; and obey ſelfe righteouſneſſe inſtead of Gods righteouſneſſe; and ſo cover themſelves with filthy Raggs inſtead of ever laſting righteouſneſſe. But all who will know true obedience, muſt firſt know a meaſure of Gods Spirit in the light of Jeſus, and therein moveing and drawing towards Chriſt Jeſus, wherein the faith is, which laies hold on Gods righteouſneſſe which is in Chriſt Jeſus, and by the moving of this Spirit in the light, the truth is ſeene, and the obedience, that is one in Chriſt Jeſus the ſecond <hi>Adam;</hi> And as the Creature is joyned in the light to that Spirit of Chriſt, and in believing, there is the life of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus made manifeſt, quickning the body unto that one obedience, which is contrary to the will of man; and the mind being kept ſpirituall in the meaſure the ſeed is raiſed, and the new is borne, of that Spirit to which ſeed the promiſe, and power is, wherein the creature is joyned heire with Chriſt Jeſus, who is Gods righteouſneſſe: and ſo in the faith is the glad tydings of good things preached to the ſoule, and by the power of the Goſpel preached to the creature; the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of God is revealed from faith to faith, and the juſt lives in that faith; and Chriſt is manifeſt for obedience to the faith: and all that are in this faith, are in the one obedience, which is in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; which he learned of the Father for us; that in that obedience
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118947:22"/>
many may be made righteous, and all that learnes Chriſt learnes his obedience, which was, not what he ſee or heard from men, but what he ſaw and heard of the Father; not in his own time or will, but in the Fathers: nor in his own ſtrength, could he do any thing, but what he ſee the Father do, in that worke he was found, doing the ſame, as he was taught of the Father in his obedience to him; not what the Scribes and Phariſees did, though they ſat in <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeat, nor what the world approved; but what was contrary to all the world, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his own will; onely ſubmitting to the moving of the Spirit of the Father that dwelt in him, by which alone he was to be guided, and furniſhed to every good work.</p>
               <p>And all that believe in him and follow his light, he leads into the ſame knowledge, and obedience, out of all carnall knowledge, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and obedience; and by faith the creature is made partaker of this obedience, and the power thereof, from faith to faith. And all that have learned him, as he is, ſo are they in this preſent world, both in law, and life, and power, and Spirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in all this in the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as he is learned: and as any comes to the unity of the faith, in him, to his meaſure ſtature and fulneſſe, ſo the obedience is but one, the power one, the way one, and the Son one, and the Father one. And this is not any thing from without, but in Spirit it is learned, and obtained, and the myſtery of it is hid from all who are without, and the miniſtration of it is ſpirituall, within, whereby that obedience is known which is to the truth through the Spirit, which is in life and not in imitation; in the will of God, and not in ſelf will, which obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſtands not in any thing ſeen from man, or by man done, thereby to imitate, or doe the like, for that is two obediences; but it ſtands in Chriſt Jeſus, and in his one obedience to the Father, ſeene in the light and in the faith received, whereby the believer is made one in it, and it in him, that as the ſame Father calls for the ſame obedience in Spirit ſo in the ſame Spirit doth the believer offer up himſelf, and all he hath in the ſame power and obedience in Chriſt Jeſus. And ſo as the creature by faith partakes of that one obedience, in the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> he is made righteous, and no further; even as all are made ſinners as they partake of the diſobedience of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and no further.</p>
               <p>And who knows to partake of this obedience, knows the eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in which all the Children of God have been taught, and enabled to this one obedience, in their ſeveral meaſures, ever ſince the world was; which is not works by them done, but the everlaſting righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, obeyed in that Spirit, according to the motions thereof ſeene in the light of Chriſt, which none knows who are heart-blind, and who minds the motions of the fleſh, and obeys them, their minds being gone out to carnall pleaſures, the Call to this obedience is not by them heard, nevertheleſſe the ſame carnall Spirit that leads out into the world, teaches to make an imitation of this obedience, and ſo deceives the ſimplicity, by ſetting up a likeneſſe without life; and ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118947:22"/>
glories in appearance, but not in heart. And the witneſſe of God in the heart or Conſcience of ſuch, teſtifying to the face of truth that their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is not perfect nor accepted, they conclude that there can be no perfect obedience attained in this world; they not knowing the mighty powerful working of God in Spirit, which worketh in them perfectly who believe and walk in the light; whereby ſuch become his workmanſhip in Chriſt Jeſus wrought into his obedience, and his obedience into them, in their meaſure, till they become of one heart, one mind, one ſoul, one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, one fleſh, and bone, and blood, and one obedience, and one life, that it is no more we that lives, but Chriſt that lives in us; and the life that we now live is by Faith in the Son of God: and though the fulneſſe of this obedience is not attained at once, yet the leaſt meaſure of it is perfect, and accepted; and ſo accepted, in him, in whom it is wrought, as the obedience of a Child is as pure, clear, and willing, as the ſtrong mans; even ſo is the new Birth in Chriſt Jeſus, according to what God requires thereof, who never requires, but what he gives; and never gives, but what is perfect; and what he perfectly accepts, which gifts are all in his Son; and in him, the leaſt is accepted, and every one that therein exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe themſelves without mixture.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning good Works.</head>
               <p>AS there is but one good, ſo there is but one Worker of good in Heaven, and in Earth, who by the Word of his Power, made all good in the beginning; and in this good Work, and Will, was Man wrought in the Will of God: in his Image and goodneſſe he ſtood; but falling from this ſtedfaſtneſſe that was in God, and be taking him unto ſelf, thereby to become wiſe, he became ſubtill and proud in himſelf, ſeeking to be as God, was caſt out from God, his Power, Love, and goodneſſe; and being fallen into the dark Imaginary of his own heart, and finding himſelf under the Curſe (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Light of Chriſt in the Conſcience is a Witneſſe) he hath ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to make a likeneſſe of God, &amp; Chriſt, and Gods Worſhip; and good Works, Faith, Hope, Patience, Love, &amp;c. but being under the powers of darkneſſe, neither knows God, nor his Work; but is deceived by the Prince of Darkneſſe, and ſo doth pleaſe himſelf with an Imitation of God, and his Work, but without power; and ſo, as he imagines, is doing good: but the teſtimony of God in his heart, bears witneſſe againſt him, that his Work is not perfect, nor accepted. He alſo imagines that he is redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118947:23"/>
but is ſtill under the commanding power of Satan, led Captive at his will; who, that he may the more ſtrongly blind him, he leads him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times into a ſeeming worſhip, that ſo he may not ſo much ſuſpect his way, nor be too much troubled at his other unrighteous practices: ſo that the worſt of men in this ſtate, have a worſhip; and each ſort thinks they are right; though there be but one way,, and they all without it; and each, in their thoughts, are not ſo bad as others; but have their ſeverall good works, though there be but one good work, and they all out of it in their own works.</p>
               <p>And it is no ſmall work to undeceive the leaſt of theſe who are thus conceited, though men of greater wits and parts (as they call them, which is but a higher deceipt) may lead them from one deceipt to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yet all the worlds wiſdome cannot bring them into the good work, nor the way wherein it is wrought. Onely ſuch who mind the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> light of Chriſt in their dark hearts, which manifeſts to them their Evill deeds, and reproves them for them, and can believe it to be the light of Chriſt, and thereto take heed to follow it out of the world, and carnall mindedneſſe, and in that light wait, till the Living-Word they come to receive in their hearts, onely ſuch come into the good work and will of God: For without the Word was nothing made, nor without it can any be redeemed: For it is the Word of the Lord, heard and received, that quickens the Dead, and raiſes to Life that which is dead in the treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes and ſins; and the Spiritual man being quickned, the power of the Word brings forth in him, the work of Gods righteouſneſſe, which was from everlaſting; which, in the meaſure thereof, confirms the Creature unto God in righteouſneſſe, who loſt the Image in unrighteouſneſſe: and ſo is the Creature renewed in the Spirit of the mind, and inward parts, to receive wiſdom and power in the hidden man, how to eſcape the evil, and reſiſt it, and to bring to light what God begets in the heart; and ſo the new Creature is ſeen created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, to walk therein, as was fore-ordained.</p>
               <p>And as the Believer is found diligent in the light, waiting, and in the Spirit obedient to this work, in this work he comes ſtill more to learn Gods Power and Teaching, and Chriſts obedience, and Gods wiſdome and care over him, in leading into the ſufferings, and tribulations, tryals and temptations, and the Faith and Fellowſhip with Chriſt therein; in which, if the creature ſtand, not a hair can fall, but he is ſure to come out more pure then gold; and ſo in all this work, he grows in the knowledge of Chriſt, and his Sonſhip, toward the meaſure, and ſtature, and fulneſſe of the perfect man, into the likeneſſe of God. And thus the Saints were made conformable to God by his mighty working, whereby he wrought powerfully in them, after his good pleaſure, contrary to their fleſhly pleaſures. And what is thus wrought, is good, becauſe it comes from the Fountain of all good; and this is not a new work, but the everlaſting good work of God, manifeſt to the Creature, and through
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118947:23"/>
the Creature to the World; by which God is glorified, who is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Author, and Finiſher thereof in every one that believes.</p>
               <p>And this is no ſelf-work; nor can it be wrought in any but where ſelf is denyed, and a Croſſe to ſelf taken up: ſo boaſting is excluded, the Creature having nothing but what he hath received, neither by his own Will nor Deed, but by believing in the Light, and in obedience of Faith.</p>
               <p>And with this Faith and Work are all the world judged, who are in their own works; and all that are without works, whoſe Faith is dead, and to every good work reprobate: And whoſe works are their own, their prayers are abomination; where the Works come not from this one everlaſting Work and Workings. For though there be many Works, as to the Creatures obedience and meaſures, yet they all compleat but this one work of the Creatures Redemption, and Gods praiſe therein, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and end of all.</p>
               <p>And of this work of God is all the world ignorant who are preaching, preſſing, and acting their good works, (as they call them) but all their works do not manifeſt a Power that brings them out of ſinne, and the worlds Conformity, and ſervice thereof in his ways and worſhip: but every good work of God in his Saints, who become obedient to his work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as they ſubject to bring forth the good work and will of God; every work begets the Creature nearer to God, and into his likeneſſe and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and this is the reward of good works to every one who are exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therein, that thereby they are wrought out of the worlds likeneſſe and conformity, and ſo out of their friendſhip, till all manner of evil they ſuffer for the name of God that is in them, and the nature of his works, which is abomination to the Worlds works, and the world to them. And ſo their name being caſt out as evil among men, they are received into the love of the Father of the Work, for which they are hated of the world; and ſo the reproach of the world becomes great riches to all who love God, and are obedient to his work, which none who ſtands in their own wills can inherit.</p>
               <p>And ſo ſelf-works, and Gods works, are manifeſt in the light. The one is, that which men ſee, or hear, or imagine, and ſo ſet themſelves to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the ſame in their own Wills, and Ways, which they have conceived in their fallen wiſdome, and earthly minds; not in Spirit new born, but in the old letter, or tradition from men: But Gods works are thoſe which are from everlaſting, before the Will of Man, or the Worlds Cuſtoms; and therefore muſt conform to neither: but every one who into this Work will come, muſt deny the world, and their own Wills; and all that is in them muſt bow, and conform to the motion of the Spirit, and to its Workings, (which is ſeen to ſuch as in the Light dwels) and in its way and time, muſt bring forth the fruits of the Spirit in due ſeaſon: not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the works of the fleſh, nor to the fleſh; but the working of the Spirit to God, in the ſight of God; and the praiſe of ſuch is not of the world, who bring not forth to the World; but of God, who bring forth to God; and the World praiſes it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> own.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:118947:24"/>
               <head>Concerning Election, and Reprobation.</head>
               <p>THis is that which is Sealed from all the world; nor can any know it, nor receive it who is in the reprobate ſtate; though many be diſputing about it in the dark; which none know but the children of light. So, as one who have obtained favour to have this myſtery revealed, I ſhall according to permiſſion write a few words, as is received in Jeſus, yet can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by no mans wiſdom, nor any who are born after the fleſh, but who knows what it is to walk in the Spirit, ſhall witneſs me here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
               <p>And I deny all of that Spirit who would fooliſhly Charge God to have concluded the condemnation of ſome perſons before they come into the world; and, though they ſeek after God, yet they cannot be ſayed, becauſe God hath purpoſed the contrary: And on the contrary, ſome are concluded to ſalvation, though they live and dye in their ſins. And this is the Spirit of the world which knowes not the ſecrets of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in Spirit, and therefore judges from the letter, from the figures, and ſhadows, but knows not the uprightneſs that lyes in the myſtery; but being without, ſo he imagins. But none knows the purpoſe of God but who comes to the beginning; for in the beginning was the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and reprobation eſtabliſhed, by an eternal decree unalterable in the two ſeeds, that after the fleſh, and that after the Spirit; and he that can Judge of theſe two, he knows the two veſſels, ordained to honour and diſhonour: and as every one is found in theſe, ſo is Gods purpoſe touching them.</p>
               <p>Now in the fall, all are in the diſhonour, and ſo children of wrath under the curſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heirs thereof, and ſo without God, or the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe: and ſo not having the in-dwelling of God no veſſels of honour but reprobate concerning God, Now Chriſt Jeſus is the election, and the elect ſeed; in whom the election is obtained, and in whom alone it is eſtabliſhed; and in the midſt of all the diſhonour his light is ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to lead out of the diſhonour, the curſe, and the fall: and whatſoever he be that will believe in his light, without reſpect of perſon, he leads out of the world: And to the cleanſing and purging, the body ſoul and mind, till the veſſell be changed, from the oldneſſe of the will, and affections and luſts of the fleſh, till the newneſs of the Spirit be witneſſed, and ſo the creature in heart and minde is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118947:24"/>
brought out of the fleſh, wherein the diſhonour lodges: and which is prepared for diſhonour; and is brought to live in the Spirit, where the luſts of the fleſh is not fulfilled; &amp; ſo the veſſel of honour is witneſſed, prepared for the maſters uſe; Who while he lived in the fleſh, was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for diſhonour, and fitted for deſtruction; Not knowing the maſter, nor his uſe, though God with much long ſuffering endure ſuch veſſels, that he may at his pleaſure ſhew his wrath thereon, who will not own the merey ſhewed in his Son. And for this purpoſe had he long endured <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> ſuffered his oppreſſion, till he was fit to ſhew his power upon him; who had long been ſetting himſelf above the ſeed of God. As alſo he did the <hi>Amorites,</hi> till their iniquities were full; and ſo doth many at this day, who proceed to one wickedneſs after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, till they fill up their meaſure, that he may make known his wrath upon them that will not own his ſeed.</p>
               <p>And ſo ſhall it be with all, who owne not the light of Chriſt, and whoſe day of viſitation is paſt; ſuch hath a meaſure of ſin to fill up in the other ſeed, which they ſhall not paſſe. And for this purpoſe is that ſeed raiſed up, and prepared, that he may ſhew his power upon him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who doth not retain the knowledge of God; that they all might be damned who take pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe, ſerving the creature more then the Creator, whoſe hearts are filled with all laſciviouſneſſe, and fleſhly luſts: and theſe are the veſſels of diſhonour. But if any man purge himſelf from theſe, he ſhall be a veſſel unto honour, Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and meet for the maſters uſe, and prepared unto every good work, which they who live in theſe things are to the good work reprobate; to God, and to the faith of God. And ſo here is the Election and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, they that are the after the Spirit, and they that are after the fleſh: and they thar are after the fleſh are not the ſeed, but they that are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſpirit are accounted for the ſeed, and theſe have obtained, but the reſt are hardned. And ſo there is no unrighteouſneſs with God, but the unrighteouſneſſe is with men, who reject the Counſel of the Lord againſt themſelves, and chuſe to abide in that which God hath curſed, and wherein, all muſt be hardned to their own deſtruction, notwithſtanding all their indevours, and labours, prayers, and teares that are in this nature, its not accepted: this being the ſeed which God hath put the emnity in, againſt his own ſeed, it cannot be well pleaſing to him. For in this he hath placed his diſpleaſure, but in the other mercy wherein he is well pleaſed for his mercies ſake: So it is not of him that wills, nor of him that runs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but of him that hath ſhewed mercy; and this mercy hath he ſet above all his works: ſo he that ſtayes in the world cannot obtain it, but the light which leads out of the world, leads up to it; and whoſoever comes unto him he will in no wiſe caſt off: but who comes not to him are caſt off already, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will not come to the light of life.</p>
               <p>So, read your condemnation, you vain babblers who ſpend your time with diſputing about Election with your reprobate mindes. When ye
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118947:25"/>
find that the light of Chriſt condemns you for your luſts, and earthly delights and the Spirit of God moves in you againſt your evil deeds, but you will not be obedient thereto, but you ſtill harden your hearts againſt the light, that is the reprobate ſtate; and that is the Spirit of God that ſtrives in thee againſt it, which would not thou ſhould dye in it; then let that of God in thy conſcience judge if thy deſtruction be not of thy ſelf, whoſe way is reprobate from God: and let that of God in thy own conſcience which reproves thee for thy wickedneſſe, be a witneſſe againſt thee that God delights not in thy deſtruction, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that thou ſhould repent; and ſo hath given thee his light to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thee and lead thee to repentance, ſhewing that he hath not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded thy condemnation before thou waſt born: And let the ſame light which checks thee for thy ſin, and lets thee ſee in thy heart that the righteous God hath appointed a day wherein all ſhall receive after their doings, be a witneſſe againſt thy vain thoughts, that God hath not concluded to quit thee in thy wickedneſſe; nor do thy ſelfiſh imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions make thy ſins any leſſe in Gods accompt. And ſo the righteous Judge of all the earth will proceed to do righteouſneſſe. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to make way for the ſame, hath he placed his pure light in the heart of every one that will minde it, which will clearly ſhew you all, whether you be in the elect ſeed, or in the ſeed of evil doers; and this light is that which being believed and followed, doth reveal the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Reprobation, and without it none knows who is Elected or Reprobated, nor can judge thereof: but if the light be minded it will reprove the Reprobate and his way, (which is contrary to God in his own heart,) for his own works, but whoſe work is wrought in God, with the light, is juſtified.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning the New Birth.</head>
               <p>THere is the Old Man, and a New Man, which is known in the light; and their ſeveral Births, and their ſeveral Natures, and Kindreds, according to that whereof they are born: That which is born of the Earth, is earthly, fleſhly, carnal, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, and this is the ſtate of the Old Man, and all that are in that ſtate are fallen from God, and his Covenant, and are in the Curſe, and wholly blind in heart, as touching the myſteries of God; yet in the ſenſual wiſdome of the fleſh, make profeſſion of God and his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118947:25"/>
but being heart-blind, neither knows God, nor his Power; but is alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from the life of God, and led Captive in the dark at his Will, who is the Prince of Darkneſſe: and what ever he doth is curſed in this ſtate. And in this ſtate did <hi>Cain</hi> ſacrifice, but could not be accepted; for he was out of the ſtate of well-doing, or well-being, yet would have been accepted: And in this ſtate <hi>Eſau</hi> ſought the bleſſing, and wept for it, but could not obtain it: And in this ſtate came <hi>Nicodemus</hi> to Chriſt; but could not enter into the Kingdom in that ſtate, nor knew the new Birth, though he loved Chriſt, and believed him to be ſent of God: And this is that ſtate <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of, when he ſaith, <hi>If I regard iniquity, God will not hear my prayer.</hi> And in this ſtate you all are, who are worſhipping in your carnal minds, and ſenſual wiſdome in the fleſh.</p>
               <p>But that which is born of the Heavenly, is Heavenly, Spiritual, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and incorruptible; which is the ſtate of the New man, which of God is begotten of the Divine Nature: and as is his Nature, ſo is his Works; and ſo his delights are Spiritual, as he is Spiritual; for as is the Man, ſo are his Works; and as is the Tree, ſo is his Fruit: and ſo, he that is born of this Seed, is born of God; and he that is born of God, ſins not, in whom that Seed remains. And all who remain in this Seed, and it in them, this hath the Promiſe and Power that puts off the Old Man with his Deeds, Luſts, and Affections; and ſo the body of ſinne being put off through the body of Chriſt, the Redemption is witneſſed; and as the Creature paſſeth from the Old to the New, ſo they paſſe from the Death to the Life; for the life is in the new, and ſo the victory is received in the new, over ſinne, the grave, and hell, which the Worlds Birth talkes of in their fallen Nature, but cannot receive the Power and Victory whereby to enter into that Kingdome, nor ſee the glory of it, and ſo takes up their reſt, and delights in viſible things and ſo encum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers themſelves with that the end whereof is deſtruction; which thoſe who are born of the ſpirit tread upon, and cannot ſet their mindes upon, nor bow unto, nor be conformable to ſuch vanities. And ſo thoſe who are of the heavenly cannot have communion with the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they being contrary minded, in all things. So that which is wiſdom to the one is fooliſhneſſe to the other, and ever was.</p>
               <p>So the Spirituall ſeed could never worſhip the heathen Gods nor can it bow to their imaginations, for that ſeed which is of God, leads the heart upto God; and that which is of the earth to earthly things: and ſo thoſe that are the children of God are lead by his ſpirit, of which they are born; and the children of this world, by the Spirit of this world are Captivated into the worlds wayes, and faſhions, and love of it, wherein is the Serpents ſeate, and kingdom; in which he rules, and wherein his power is ſeen in all who are diſobedient to the light of Chriſt the new man; ſo being given up (becauſe of the blindneſſe of their hearts) to his power, which is alwayes in the dark, in ſuch he brings forth his enmity againſt, the babes of God born after the Spirit, children of the light, of the immortal ſeed, who bear the image of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118947:26"/>
inviſible God, and have the Spirituall worſhip, into which they are led and guided with the eternal ſpirit, of which they are born; which can no longer ſtay in any form of worſhip then God ſtayes therein; but by his Spirit is led to follow him into whatever he goes, and out of what ever he departs: which thoſe who are born after the fleſh, and ſee but the out-ſide, and form, and there abides when God is departed, ſuch are the ſeat of Satan become, where he ſitts and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutes ſuch as follow the Spirits teaching, into its ſeveral miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; And therein hath the ſerpent beguiled the creature, by getting into ſomewhat of the form once uſed with the Saints (whilſt God dwelt therein,) and to that adds inventions of his own, called De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and Order, and the like, and with this hath deceived the creatures, ſo as to ſerve his ends, to ſhed the blood of their bretheren, under a pretence of error, and blaſphemy, and denying Ordinances, and worſhips, and as being leaders of dangerous Sects and Hereſies, denying government, turning the world upſide down, and the like: So that the childreu of light have been ever numbred amongſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors, but were never ſo, further then to transgreſſe the wills of men to obſerve the will of God: yet none of theſe did ever ſuffer as well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers in the worlds accompt, but as not worthy to live in the world, being born of a principle above the world, which the natural man knows not. So he that is born after the fleſh perſecutes him that is born after the ſpirit, as it is at this day, thinking they do God ſervice becauſe they know not the Father, nor the Son, but live in darkneſſe, nor owning that whereof the children of light is born, ſo becomes their enemies.</p>
               <p>And this is your ſtate who reſiſt that meaſure of light that ſhines in your dark hearts, that ſhews your evil deeds. So being againſt the light of the Spirit, you are enimies to all who of that Spirit are born. And ſo farr as you ſee the ground &amp; root of your diſobedience to the light in your ſelves that reproves of ſin, ſo farr you may ſee the ground of your emnity, and no farther. And untill you joyn to that light you cannot be one with<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſeed, but hate it; for that which is born of the will of the fleſh is emnity to that which is born of the will of God; and that which is born of God is emnity with the world, and conformity to it. And with the light are you Judged to be of the fleſh who love the things of the fleſh, and minde them; and who conform to this world are of it: what ever you profeſſe to the contrary, the light will find you out; which light leads above all theſe things up to the Father of light; which light is one with all who are born of the Spirit, but a witneſſe againſt you who are born of the fleſh. So they that are in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God, that in your conſcience is witneſs, the light which is condemnation. But who is born of the Spirit, with ſuch he is well pleaſed, the teſtimony of their conſcience bearing them witneſſe in the ſight of God, that they are his Children, and born of him; and their envy, and reproch, and ſuffering from the world for teſtifing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118947:26"/>
the deeds thereof, are as a cloud of witneſſes that they are not of it, for it loves its own, and ſo the enmity is ſeene put betweene the ſeeds; that of the Serpent ſeeks a word, or a forme without, whereby to murther, and deſtroy the creature that God hath made, under a pretence of ſerving God; but the ſeed of God ſtrikes at the head of that enmity, and roote of ſin, but ſaves the work of God alive.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning the <hi>Baptiſm</hi> of Chriſt, from that the world ſo calls</head>
               <p>IN the world there be many forts and forms of Baptiſmes; but in Chriſt there is but one, and that is that of the Spirit, and this is the Baptiſme of Chriſt, and all that are baptiſed with it, are baptiſed into his death, buried with him unto the world, its wayes and worſhips, loves, and freindſhips, and to all that in them is, which would conforme or bow thereto; and through this death is the ſeed of God raiſed up out of the grave, quickned by the ſame Spirit which raiſed Jeſus from the dead. And all that are Baptiſed with this Spirit, (and the old Man dead and buried) they are raiſed a ſpiritual ſeed unto God, holy, and zealous of good works, being begotten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of another nature from above, which is but one; and all as they are baptized herein, grow into one in God the Father, and the Son Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo the Saints were all baptiſed by one Spirit into one body, out of that nature in which all differences are, Sects, and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; and ſo come to put on Chriſt which is but one; for as many as are baptiſed unto Chriſt have put on Chriſt, and his mind and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and ſuch know a further prize then contentions about Elements of the world, or waſhings without; neither do they ſtand laying againe ſuch foundations, as ſtands in times, and ſeaſons, and cuſtoms, and perſons, as all the world is contending about, who are in the many Baptiſmes, and many faſhions; ſome contending for ſprinkling Infants <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome for dipping them; ſome for ſprinkling them over againe; and ſome for dipping them over againe; when they are growne to ſuch a confuſion in outward words; and many other outward Ceremonies they keepe themſelves diſputing and jangling about, from the letter, in an imitation of <hi>Johas</hi> Miniſtry, calling it the Baptiſme of Chriſt; but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118947:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:118947:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:118947:28"/>
out of the Spirit and power of Chriſt or <hi>John</hi> either; yea, ſo farre from the power as not come to the forme of either.</p>
               <p>And this effect this hath taken in all, who are gone out into the world in theſe imitations and imaginations, that ſo many Baptiſmes ſo many Religions, and Sects; and every Sect, Maſter, and his followers ſet themſelves againſt all other in the way they have conceived to be right, and to that way muſt all bow, or elſe no agreement, though never ſo neare in other things: nay ſo zealous they are for their Likeneſſe, that if any come not into it, though the Spirit of God be in them, (and they themſelves confeſſe it) yet he muſt not ſpeake in that creature in their Churches, without bowing to their formes of water, which are all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent one from another, though the Spirit of God be but one, and cannot be limitted to any viſible forme or rudiment. And thus the form is ſet above the power, and not the true form neither; but as men have conceived from the letter, by the Counſels of their own braine; ſome in the Popiſh Councels, ſome ſince; but none from the Mouth of the Lord: and therefore they are ſcattered in their imaginations and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmes. But who are baptiſed with the baptiſme of the Spirit are bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed into one body. But all that are without who are the neareſt are in the error, not knowing the Scripture, nor power of God herein: For all who have not their law, guide, and rule in Spirit, are in that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration who have erred, and loſt the Saints guide; and ſuch are ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with what they from the letter imagine, into diviſions.</p>
               <p>And this was that which <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw getting in amongſt the Churches in<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 17.</note> his time, ſetting up ſects, and the perſons by whom they were baptiſed; puft up for them and againſt the other Apoſtles, ſome of <hi>Paul,</hi> ſome of <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp;c. Which <hi>Paul</hi> ſeeing, thanks God he had baptized no more of them; and plainly ſaies, Chriſt ſent him not to baptize but to<note place="margin">Which clearly ſhows, it was not laid on the Apoſtles as of neceſſity but as they found it of ſervice or diſſervice.</note> preach the Goſpel, though he could uſe it untill he ſaw them make an Idoll of it, thereby to make deviſions and parties, and to puffe up one above another, as it is now uſed at this day; yea farre more, for it is now made the key to let in, and ſhut out of that they call a Church: yea further ſome ſay none can be ſaved without it, but all that have it, are bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>evers, and ſhall be ſaved; and ſo ſet it in the place of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But others are more moderate, who finding it practiſed in the Letter they ſay it is an ordinance, and they who practiſe it not, deny an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Chriſt. To ſuch I ſay, all that is in the letter is not ordained there to be taken up by all that read it, for the Saints had their call to their particular Miniſtrations, in Spirit, and not in Letter; for elſe they had not witneſſed differences of adminiſtrations but the ſame Lord; But by the Spirit they were led from carnall adminiſtrations, and through them, not ſticking in the Letter. What letter had <hi>Paul</hi> to deny Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, which the letter ſaid, ſhould be as a ſigne for ever? Or by what letter, did he deny Baptiſme? Did he deny an Ordinance of Chriſt in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe, &amp; divers more rudiments which were commands in the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which he preached &amp; practiſe in Spirit, putting an end to the ſhadow, of things to come, and leading to the body, as is plaine <hi>Col.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:118947:28"/>Further I ſay, if it were ſo that all that was done in the letter, was to be taken up, then the forme thereof muſt not be changed, if the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be the rule; But not any that I know at this day that are in the forme as the Saints did it; for none practiſed this but who was called out to teach all Nations. So you that have your certaine dwelling places, and live in your worldly eſtates and faſhions, are out of this Call. Neither did they take ſuch into the outward waſhing, who had beene there before, but baptiſed ſuch into the name of Chriſt Jeſus with the Spirit, that they might receive the holy Ghoſt. But if you ſay they had it not in right forme and manner, nor by perſons rightly called and qualified, &amp;c: I ſay, Nor can they have that from you who are not called out of the world, but live in its friendſhip, profeſſions, faſhions, and cuſtoms in which the Saints never lived after they were called to teach and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize. So you do but add another falſe forme, to that they had before, but ſtill out of the power, nor any change of faith, or qualification; onely in that thing of Water over againe, differing in ſome circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as you have conceived from the letter, but ſtill with the reſt of profeſſions, in Covetouſneſſe, Pride, and Contention, vaine words and heatheniſh cuſtomes, and manners of the Nations, in which you live: you that can live in Suites, and revenge; you that ſweare at mens wills, and ſo deny the commands of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, whoſaies, Above all things ſweare not at all; you that can uphold the high places of Popery, which yet remaine in the land; and ſuch a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip therein as Chriſt never commanded; with tythes and offerings, and all the reſt of Popiſh inventions, whereby Chriſt is denyed comne in the fleſh the everlaſting Preiſt, and ſomthing ſet up inſtead of his way like unto the Jewiſh Preiſthood which is not it neither, but an imagined thing, from men of corrupt minds, &amp;c: You who can do theſe things, and much more of that Nature, rather then you will ſuffer the loſſe of all things, you are farre unlike thoſe you would imitate, or thoſe they baptiſed.</p>
               <p>And, were baptiſme in your manner, as great a croſſe to you now, as it was in the time of the perſecuting Jews, or as theſe other weightier things are now, we ſhould find few to contend for it, as for the other things. For did you know the right ends of that miniſtration of water, you would know that it was a forerunner of Chriſts Kingdom, and a witneſſe to all men that the Jews Ceremonies, and Heatheniſh prayers and worſhips wherein they was growne into diviſions, was to have an end, and the ſpirituall miniſtration and baptiſme was to be ſet up in the downfall of Carnall Ordinances, and Elements, of all which they were to repent, for the Kingdom of God was at hand, even within all, that would beleive it; who did deny all the Jews worſhips, circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and ordinances without in the letter; and preached them and practiſed them in Spirit, but your baptiſms which comes not to an end of tythes, and offerings, and Jewiſh Ceremonies and Gentiles alſo, that baptiſme we deny; for herein was the croſſe of Chriſt, and the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118947:29"/>
of God manifeſt; for they ſuffered for this all the envy, that Jews and profeſſors could do unto them, who upheld the ſame in the letter but denied the power and Spirit; which could they but have bowed to their ceremonies outward, the croſſe of Chriſt had ceaſed; and then the power of Chriſt had ceaſed alſo, and the ſame is now ſeene of you at this day; and the ſame croſſe. For could but thoſe whom Chriſt hath called out now bow to your ſeverall forms of baptiſmes and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips of you that be zealous for them, and bow to mens wills, and worſhip the perſons of ſuch as are zealous for their Pride, and wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, we ſhould not ſuffer by you, but the offence of the croſſe would ceaſe, as it is ceaſed to all who preach Baptiſmes, Carnall Ordinances, reſpect of perſons, conformity to mens wills; and the worlds cuſtomes, and manners; who preach up pride, ſwearing, and imperfection, and ſin for terme of life, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I ſay to you who can conforme to the wayes of men and pleaſe them, the Croſſe of Chriſt is ceaſed, and ſo the power alſo; and therefore are you ever preaching againſt the worlds wayes, and wickedneſſe, but never able to lead out of them; like thoſe who minded earthly things, who were enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt, ever learning and teaching, but never able to come to the knowledge of the truth that makes free, to thoſe the Croſſe and ſufferings is ceaſed, and they and the Powers of the Earth are one againſt ſuch as take up the Croſſe to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt in the way of the Spirit, and ſuch being without in the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter are become ſpiritually blind, and ſo cannot ſee that the appearance of Chriſt was ever croſſe to all who was got into the rudiments, plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for out-ſides, but had loſt the power, wherein this generation ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, having loſt both power and forme alſo.</p>
               <p>And to you I ſay of all ſorts of baptiſmes, as the Apoſtle ſaid of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, We are the baptiſme who worſhip God in the Spirit, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in Chriſt Jeſus, and have no confidence in the fleſh, though we might have confidence in the outward waſhing, being that we have had it from ſuch as gathered it from the letter; and yours is no more. But this we have learned, that it is not baptiſme which is outward in the fleſh, but that is Baptiſm which is in the Spirit, and not in the letter, whoſe praiſe is not of men but of God; whereby we are baptiſed by one Spirit into one body; and as many as are baptiſed into Chriſt are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed into his death, and have put him on and are become new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and this is that which availeth to ſave us, not the waſhing the fleſh but the anſwer of a good conſcience towards God by the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Jeſus.</p>
               <p>And this baptiſme, we witneſſe that whoſoever is therewith baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhall be ſaved but for other baptiſmes, which men are contending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout from the letter, we ſee the end thereof, and what they bring forth. But if any ſhould come in the power and Spirit of <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſm; or if any had a Call from God thereto, ſuch we judge not, nor gainſay; but that any hath power from the letter to take up and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118947:29"/>
it upon others (yea, though it was the true form) that I deny; or that they who are not ſent to baptize, that the leaving the outward water and going on to the Spiritual Baptiſm, is a ſleighting or contemning of an Ordinance of God, that I deny alſo: for this might as well have been charged againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> who denyed it in his time, and preached Baptiſme in Spirit, in its ſtead; the ſame thing, for which we are accuſed (to deny an Ordinance of Chriſt) whom he hath not ſent to dip or ſprinkle in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; but to preach the Goſpel of Light and Life, and the Spiritual Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of Chriſt Jeſus, to the bringing all that receive our teſtimony into one body, by one Spirit; not making diviſions about carnal things; for to us the day is come, and the ſhadows fly away.</p>
               <p>And your Baptiſme we judge and the end of it, which hath not led you out of Tythes and Offerings, Swearing Suing, and Contention, out of the Worlds Worſhips, Manners, and reſpects of Perſons; and to ſuffer the loſſe of all, to witneſſe Chriſt. That Baptiſme we ſee to be out of the Faith of Chriſt Jeſus, and not worth contending about; for he that is in the world without it, is as good as he that is in the world with it, if not much better; for that Baptiſme which preaches not repentance to all the ways of faln-man, and manners there ſet up, is none of <hi>Johns;</hi> and that which walks in the fleſh is none of Chriſts: So with the Light of Chriſt, if you it mind, you will ſee your ſelves out of the true Baptiſm, both as to Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Manner, and the End, who are crying up Ordinances in the World, which leads not out of the world; and when the world comes to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that Baptiſm will not ſave you from the worlds portion.</p>
               <p>But this I ſay to thoſe who would knew the truth herein, as we have received: we do not deſpiſe any Ordinance of God which he hath called any of his people to, in any Generation; nor dare we take a Tradition upon us, which God hath not required at our hands, leſt we keep people in that which God is departed out of; and it be ſaid to us, <hi>who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired it at your hands?</hi> But God hath ſhewed us a more excellent way; The Light is come, and therein have we found Chriſt Jeſus, the Guide of his people, and the Leader of Ages, even the Spirit of Truth, which leads into all Truth, even into all that God requires; the obedience to which, is better then Sacrifice: And to direct people to this Spirit are we ſent; that Chriſt may be all in all, who gives power in the Creature to perform in what he leads into; that thereby all that believe in the light may learn him who begets the Will and the deed alſo, who is the Author and Finiſher of their Faith, who look to him alone, and to his light, that all may ſee their righteouſneſſe to be of him alone. And by this, which we have received of him in Spirit, do we all ſee you, who read what the Saints have done by Call from God, and from that ſets your ſelves to do the like, to be in the Imitation, and ſelf-righteouſneſſe, and Will-worſhip, both in this, and all other things, into which you are not led by the Lord, and by a Call from him. For, this I ſay, that the Father hath given his Son for a Leader and Guide to all Ages, and into, and out of all Forms, at his Will, and in his way, and time, in every Generation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:118947:30"/>And therefore it is, that all who know his Will herein cannot endure that any viſible thing ſhould be ſet up, to limit his leading in Spirit, or his people from following in Spirit. So no form we deny, into which Chriſt leads in Spirit; but all forms we deny, that are uſed by Men to keep peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from following the Spirit: for thoſe onely are the Children of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 14.</note> who are led by the Spirit of God; to whom, they who are led by the<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6.</note> Letter were ever enemies; for it is the Spiritual Miniſtration that gives the knowledge of God, and his Glory, and Power; and not the literall: for he that is born after the fleſh, hath his way in the viſibles; but he that is born after the Spirit, hath his food the world knows not of, and therefore becomes his enemy. And in that ſtate you are, who takes the ſhadow to oppoſe the body, which ſhould lead to the body, which is the end of the ſhadow; And takes the Letter to oppoſe the Spirit, which<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 2. 16, 17, 20.</note> is given to declare the ſufficiency of the Spirits teaching alone; and ſo pervert the Scriptures out of their place and end; which are ſet to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie of Chriſt, the Life, and End, to ſet them in the place of Chriſt, and<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 38, 39, 40.</note> think to have life in them.</p>
               <p>And this is the errour of the Wicked, who are gone into the world; ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual, not having the Spirit. And in this ſtate, wherein the Spirit leads not, both Scriptures, and Ordinances, and all other the gifts of God are abuſed, wreſted out of their places, and made unprofitable. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you that take up from the Letter, cannot bring forth their fruits who were ſpiritually called into their ſeveral Miniſtrations: therefore your Ordinances are left to you deſolate, you and they in the world to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; out of which God is leading his people in Spirit, to get himſelf a Name, in ſuch a way as is fooliſhneſſe to your wiſdome, yet the hidden wiſdome of God to the Children of Light, who have believed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
               <p>And you that uſe great ſwelling words, crying, <hi>We deny an Ordinance of God:</hi> To you, I ſay, To neglect that which is altered from what God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, both in Call, Manner, and End, is no neglecting an Ordinance of God. 1. God never called any to baptize; but firſt he called them out of the world, and their habitations there, to follow Chriſt, as into the Wilderneſſe, which were Prophets and Apoſtles called immediatly. 2. They did not baptize Believers over again with water, who had had it, becauſe they had it not before in their faſhion; but they went to diſciple Unbelievers: Neither did they lay it upon all, as of abſolute neceſſity, but as they ſaw it uſeful, and could for bear, in caſe it was idolized. 3. Their End was to gather all into One, out of all the Shaddows and Ceremonies, and Faſhions of the World, to follow Chriſt alone, as he walked, bearing his Croſſe daily, ſuffering the ſpoyling of their goods joyfully, and their lives unto death, rather than to conform to any but him alone for whoſe ſake they were hated of all men; which end, how your Baptiſms anſwers, let your Pride, and Pleaſures and Conformity to the world, in their Faſhions, Manners, and Worſhips, and upholding thereof; your Suits, and Contentions about carnal things, your Rents and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118947:30"/>
Diviſions, about outward Forms of Baptiſms, and Worſhips; and uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that in others, which you know is falſe, by Tythes and Offerings, whereby Chriſt is denyed, and the Popiſh Inventions holden up, with much ſuch like: I ſay, That theſe things judge you before all men, and the light in your Conſcience anſwers thereto, untill the Lord appear to judge your unfaithfulneſſe herein.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning the Lords Supper.</head>
               <p>THis is the thing that all the Worlds Profeſſors are contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about; and, indeed, is of great uſe and profit to the weak Believers, who have not yet ſeen the Lord, for bringing them all into one body and bloud, mind and heart, and ſoul and ſpirit: But ſince the Myſtery of Iniquity began to work, the Worlds Teachers and Profeſſors having loſt their in-dwelling in the body of Chriſt, are run out into the Imaginations, and are ſo far from the life of this, as that they have loſt the Form, and the firſt Inſtitution, as as it was by Chriſt firſt performed and appointed; and therefore are ſo far from being thereby made one in the blood of Chriſt, that they are ſhedding one anothers blood about the Form, which they are all out of, and have loſt, and the power alſo: For this was done and inſtituted by<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 26.</note> Chriſt, as they ſate at meat, and did eat; and ſo often as they did eat and drink thereof, they were to do it in remembrance of him, ſhewing his<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 14. 22</note> death, till he came.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 26.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And this was that the Apoſtles received of the Lord, and was ſo pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in the purity of the Church, before they ran into confuſion; which did continue ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine, and Fellowſhip, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bread, and prayer, daily breaking bread from houſe to houſe, did eat their meat with gladneſſe, and ſingleneſs of heart, in the fear and favour of God: And this was to be done at all Seaſons, when they eat and<note place="margin">Act. 2. 41. to the end.</note> drank: in their eating and drinking they were to do it to the Lord, and therein to have Communion with his Body, and his Blood; and for that<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note> end, were to keep themſelves pure from all pollution: yea, when they<note place="margin">15. <hi>to the end.</hi>
                  </note> were to eat with Gentiles, they were to partake of the Table of the Lord, as is plain, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 &amp; therefore they were to keep their Conſciences pure from things offered to Idols; for they could not partake of the Table of the Lord, and eat that which was ſacrificed to Devils; though, in ſome
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118947:31"/>
Caſes, they might go to a Feaſt among Unbelievers; yet whether they eat or drank, they were to do it to the Lord, as at his Table; and not as at the Table of Gentiles, whoſe feaſting is in the Luſt, and ſo their meat they ſacrifice to Devils, and eat not to God; and ſo do all who eat to the luſt: To keep from which, there is no other thing can, but to eat in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of Chriſts death till he come; who, when he is come; he takes the ordering and government of the Creature himſelf upon his ſhoulders, and ſo ever keeps them out of the luſt in all they do: and ſo is the Creation reſtored and reconciled to God in Chriſt Jeſus at his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing: till which time, the Apoſtles exhorted to theſe things, and warned of the contrary; as <hi>Jude,</hi> who ſaw ſome crept in among the Church, who did turn the grace of God into laſciviouſneſſe, walking after their own hearts luſts, whereby they defile the fleſh, living in ſenſuality, not having the Spirit to order them, they fed themſelves without fear, and theſe were ſpots in their Feaſts; who being once inlightened, and again giving way to the luſts and exceſſe, they became twice dead, pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked up by the roots; yet had they great ſwelling words. And of ſuch like, are many Examples at this day: who have had ſomething quickned in them to hope for the appearance of the Lord; but fulneſſe and exceſſe having overtaken them, for want of eating alwayes in fear, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his coming, they are become dead again to any hope of his appearance at the preſent; and have put his coming afar off into<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 5, 6.</note> another world; yet are contending about the Shadows or Figures of his coming, as they have imagined concerning them; But are become re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pil.</hi> 4. 5.</note> in the Faith, as to his appearance, and plucked up by the roots. And to avoid this, it was the Lord Jeſus commanded his Diſciples, in eating and drinking, to ſhew forth his death till he came; and they knowing this from the Lord, gave it in example and warning to thoſe who were convinced, that in all fear and moderation, they might wait for his appearance, who, at his coming, would bring to light the hidden things, and manifeſt the counſels of the heart, and all its deceipts, and become the Worker in them; and then they ſhould have praiſe of God: and theſe things were transferred to the Apoſtles in a figure: So they exhorted the Believers to whom the Lord was at hand, to let their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration be known to all men, the Lord is at hand; which they knew, All who get up into the liberty of the fleſh, rioting and exceſſe, will put afar off; as it is at this day with many, who are in Obſervations outward, who have a day to go into the Idols Temple, and there to eat Bread, and drink Wine in a Self-ſolemnity, once a moneth, or three times a year, or as they imagine: ſome affirming the Body and Blood of Chriſt to be in the Creature after Conſecration, (as they call it) ſome ſaying: Nay, but it is Spiritual after Conſecration: Others ſaying, It is ſtill carnall, and not changed, becauſe of words; and one imagines the body of Chriſt reall in it: another, not reall; but by Faith, (as they ſay:) But, in this, they all agree, that they return back into the pleaſures of the fleſh, and faſhions of the world, there to eat and drink the reſt of Gods
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118947:31"/>
Creatures, to ſpend on their luſts; and it muſt needs be ſo with ſuch as do not diſcern his body in their eatings who is the body of all Creatures, and filleth all things in Heaven and in Earth: which they who ſtick in Obſervations never knew; and with ſuch he is alwayes to come, or paſt. But the carnall eye which ſtickes in the Viſibles can never ſee him preſent, to order the Creation out of the Luſt, and therefore it is that all the Creatures of God are turned to feed the Luſt, in that ſtate, as is ſeen in all the Worlds Profeſſion; and therefore accurſed: the more riches the more pride, the more fullneſſe the more luſt, in that ſtate where; Chriſt is not diſcerned preſent, And ſo their eating is not the Supper of the Lord, nor doth he ſup with them in the New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>but in the luſtfull Spirit become the table of the Devill, where the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are Sacrificed to his uſe; ſo he keeps them in obſervation of a day from the letter, which they think is worſhip, but he bears rule in their whole lives by his Spirit, and ſo much of the Creation as is in their hands, is uſed at his will. Aud hence is all laſciviouſneſſe, wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſtrife, fighting, Suites and Violence, Sports and Vanities, too many here to mention, all with the Creation is ſpent upon, (given not to that end) for which they ſhall account who are in that ſtate, when ſhall be required his Corn, and his Wine, his Wooll and his Flax, which he hath made for his uſe, and to be ordered by his Son, who is the fullneſſe and vertue of every Creature, which all know who come to his Supper, where the Father and the Son are come in, and Supp with the Creature, which all the imitaters and obſervers of times are ignorant of: whoſe contention is about out-ſides.</p>
               <p>And for the ſake of ſuch who are loſt in this thing, and troubled in minde concerning it, what I have received of the Lord that I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto you, which all ſhall witneſſe to, who come to pertake thereof, as the truth is in Chriſt Jeſus, If you intend to ſupp with the Lord, or ſhew the Lords death till he come, let your Eating and Drinking, ſo oft as you do it, be in remembrance of him; and in his feare, that at death you may witneſſe to the luſt, and exceſſe; which is that which ſlew him, ſince the Foundation of the World; And is the great enemy of his appearance; and that by which he lies ſlain in the great City which is called <hi>Sodom</hi> &amp; <hi>Egypt.</hi> For all you that live in pleaſure on the Earth, and are wanton; you that nouriſh your hearts as in the day of ſlaughter, you have condemned and killed the Juſt, and he doth not reſiſt you: and you muſt know a death to this, before you can Supp with the Lord, or he with you: But if you eat in remembrance of him, and ſo come to dye to that which ſlue him, then do you ſhew the Lords death till he come: and when he comes he ſhall not find you eating and drinking with the drunken nor beating your fellow-ſervants.</p>
               <p>And this is known from the Lord in the Eternall, to be the true end of the Supper of the Lord, inſtituted and appointed, that in the remembe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his death they might be kept from all exceſſe, that at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they be found fit to receive him; which they who feed without fear
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118947:32"/>
do deny, and crucifie afreſh to themſelves. And therefore in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, ſpeaking of his coming, he warnes them to take heed leaſt at any time in eating their hearts be overcharged with ſurfetting, and drunkenneſſe, and cares of this life, and ſo that day come upon them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares; and ſo become a ſnare unto them: for ſo it is to all who are in that State, when he ſhould appeare unto them; and they cannot receive the day of his viſitation, whoſe hearts are gone out into theſe carnall things: And this he knew, that till That man be born which lives not by bread alone, That man that lives upon the Creatures is ſo one drawn into them, and ſo to forgett his coming who is the maker thereof, who is the Sanctifier thereof, at his coming: and ſo orders the outward food as unto God, and not to carnall things, the minde growes thereby, and ſo to the pure all things are pure: but where the pure is not, all things are defiled, when they are not Sanctified by the word and prayer; And therefore are to be received in fear: and remembring therein his death till He come who is the word and prayer, which at his coming reſtores all things, to God, which till then are Subject to be uſed to the luſt, which was the thing Chriſt in tender love to his diſciples at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture warned them on, knowing that their nature would draw to the earth-ward, not yet being changed, nor having Chriſt born in them to keep them; and for all this his warning and leaving this as a ſigne; how ſoone were they returned into the carnalls, and to their fiſhings, and the like, having forgott the promiſe of his coming till he renewed the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memberance of it, making himſelf known in breaking of bread again af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Reſurrection? and ſo charging them to wait for his coming at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the promiſe of the Father, of which he had told them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death; which they were to ſhew, ſo often as they broke bread, till he came, and after he was come to the Apoſtles, they continued it for their ſakes who were weak in the faith, to whom he was not yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, And ſo thoſe did break bread from houſe to houſe, and eate with Singleneſſe of Heart to Chriſt, and not to the luſt; which was another thing then the Worlds Obſervation of Bread and Wine, or Wafers, in the Idols temple, where the Lords death is not ſhewed till he come; where ſome are hungry and ſome are drunken, where the Covetous, the proud, the liers, ſwearers, whoremongers, figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſewers, ſcorners, and all evil workers meet, to eate bread and wine ſo often a yeare, and returne into the luſt again; This is not to Eate the Lords Body, nor at his table, but the table of Devils.</p>
               <p>And this you ſhall all know that you that do this for an hour, or a day, and then feed without fear, not ſhewing the Lords death in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your eating, ſo oft as you eate and drink till he come, you are they who Eate Judgment to your ſelves herein; And all your will-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip will not be found at that day to be an Ordinance of Chriſt, as you have limitted it; nor can you know his coming to your Savlation. And of this Sort are you who now ſay, The Lord delayeth his coming and have put it into another generation; if not till dooms-day, as you call it:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:118947:32"/>
and ſo have ſetled your ſelves in your worldly pleaſures, and high Notions with the drunken Spirit eating and drinking, and beating your fellow-ſervants, mocking, whipping, and impriſoning them at your will and pleaſure, having forgott his coming; which if you did remember to ſhew forth his death ſo often as you eat and drink till he come, you ſhould not have been found in blindneſſe and oppoſition to his coming, (as to your ſelves) nor perſecuting him now which is come in others; nor ſhould your table have been made a ſnare unto you, that that day ſhould overtake you unawares, (as it is ſeen at this day) upon whom the Words of Chriſt are to be fulfilled.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Redemption.</head>
               <p>THis is that which many boaſt on, and glory in, who never knew what it is to be redeemed further than in words, and imagination thereof; nay there are few who are come ſo far as to know what it is that wants redemption, and that the promiſe is to, wherein onely it is ſeene and received, for there is a ſeed to which the promiſe of redemption is; but thou who takes delight in ſin, and pleads for it, art not he. Thou that can take pleaſure in the fleſh, and faſhion thy ſelfe thereto, art of another ſeed who art at liberty in the world, to conforme thy ſelfe thereto, in thy own will and way and time, who haſt power in thy hand to do what thou liſt, and when thou liſt, and as thou liſt: Thou needs no redemption who art at liberty, nor phyſitian who art not ſick; and ſo a talk of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption little changes thy condition in that State, who art of this world, and obtaines that thou loves, and therein takes pleaſure; build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a feate and bleſſing thy ſelfe therein, laying up thy treaſure here below, he that redeemes <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſeede is no glad tydings to thee, who ſpeaks woe to all in that ſtate. But if thou find ſomthing in thee, that in all theſe worldly delights cryes Vanity, and Emptyneſſe, and can find no ſatisfaction therein, nor can conforme to this world, nor take pleaſure in wickedneſſe, that cannot plead for ſin, but cryes woe to thee becauſe of thy wickedneſſe, and mornes becauſe of the abominations of thy times, wherein thou haſt followed the worlds cuſtomes, and fooliſh faſhions; if thou find that in thee that cannot take delight in decking the outſide with pride, nor feeding without feare, that cannot feed upon the viſibles, nor ſhorſhip the creature, nor bow to any but God alone, but condemns thee if thou ſo do: If thou find that which breaths in thee towards God for life, and ſtrength againſt all theſe vanities,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:118947:33"/>
and all other evills; That which would follow God out of all the world if it had power, I ſay if ſuch a ſeed thou find in thee, though it be the leaſt of all ſeeds in thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet that is the ſeed of the Kingdom, to which the promiſe is: and no further then that principle is raiſed to raigne in thee above all that is contrary to it, no further art thou redeemed by Chriſt Jeſus: for thats the plant of Gods renowne, the Lilly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the thornes; which with the Cares of this world, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptfullneſſe of riches, and pleaſures, is choaked that it cannot bring forth to God, who hath placed it in thee for himſelfe, that therein he might teach thee to profit, and from thence thou might receive wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and ſtrength, yea all that is needfull for thee in thy meaſure to which thou art called.</p>
               <p>And this lying under thy luſts and pleaſures is the cauſe thou knows not God the Father, nor the Son; for to this he is revealed, though thou talke of redemption, yet thou knows not God, nor his power, nor life, nor perſence with thee to guide thee out of the evill, and to give the victory over the Prince of this world, and his dominion; but art captivated at his will, to do his works; and ſo under the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that he is in; and the talke of redemption doth not deliver thee from his temptations; but into it thou falls, and commits the ſin that is of his moving, and ſo art of the Devill; but that which is of God lies under in death, and captivity, and bonds of iniquity; and ſo thou canſt not have power, nor the promiſe, nor ſalvation, which in the ſeed is placed, which is not of thee; nor with thee, while thou art in theſe delights but againſt thee, and thou ſinning againſt it; and ſo art not of the promiſed ſeed, but an enemy to it, and by thy luſts and pleaſures, and ſelf-will, art in <hi>Pharoahs</hi> ſtate, and nature, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſeed of God in the houſe of bondage; and doſt not pittie nor regard the cryes thereof, which cryes againſt thy pride and exceſſe, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie and wrath, and all thy wickedneſſe, by which thou oppreſſeſt the ſeed of God in thee, (in that ſtate where death raignes) for which the wrath of God comes upon the world of iniquity; who are enemies to that ſeed which is of the Covenant; and are not joyned to it, (but to the contrary, in the contrary nature) to which all who are joyned in the light, come to pertake of Gods love, and life therein by Jeſus Chriſt; who takes upon him that ſeed after the fleſh, not the ſeed of the evill one, nor the nature of Angels, but the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to whom the promiſe is,</p>
               <p>And all who know this, quickned and raiſed by the Spirit of Jeſus, know the plant of Gods renowne, of Gods own planting, in which the fruit is found; and ſuch knows where to waite for a ſupply of all wants, and counſell in all ſtraits; where is the law received that is ſpirituall, and the righteouſneſſe of ſaith, revealed from faith to faith; from which Gods righteouſneſſe is manifeſt in the world; not of ſelfe, nor ſelf-works, nor of that ſeed, but of the heritage of faith, a free gift to the ſeed. And in this ſeed as it is redeemed hath the Saints fellowſhip
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:118947:33"/>
with the Father, and the Son in the light and all the gifts and grace, whereby that creature becomes free from the law of ſin that they be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to Chriſt, in him to ſerve the living God, ſet free from the ſervice of ſin and Satan; And this is their freedom even their righteouſneſs, which is everlaſting as the ſeed is redeemed out of the pit; For where this ſeed is raiſed up, there the creature receives from God of his fulneſs but where the ſeed is in the grave, the curſe is betwixt, upon him where the ſin is and the treſpaſſes, by which it is ſlain; But where this is raiſed the creature is bleſſed of God for the ſeeds ſake, throughout all the Nations of the Earth which layes this ſeed: for in this is God worſhipped, but where this is dead the ſacrifice is abomination, for they that are in the grave cannot Praiſe God; its the living that he accepts and not the dead.</p>
               <p>And this I ſay to all you who find ſuch a thing as is holy, thus moving in you againſt your luſts and worldly pleaſures, Take heed and do not deceive your ſelves with a talk of redemption while this is in priſon, and not brought above all your luſts; But in the light of Chriſt waite which lets you ſee this, that you may ſee his power in ſpirit to raiſe this to raign above all in you that is contrary, &amp; ſo ſhall you raign with it ov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er all the world, and its wicked wayes: but if you have found this breathing towards God, and you have no regard thereto, take heed leſt he that gave this for thy ſalvation, take it away from thee in wrath and leave thee to thy luſts without reproof; (For his Spirit will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſtrive with you.) And then it had been good you had not been born. And this hath befallen many after many reproofes and motions to good; Who now are left to fill up their meaſure with greedineſſe; Who now glory in their ſhame, and boaſt of their filthyneſſe: and this day is coming upon many more, who now little minde the meaſure of God moving in them; but live in the luſt, ſinning againſt their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, out of the ſelfe ends; And yet pleaſe themſelves with a talke of redemption: As the greateſt profeſſion now ſet up by many, is to make the redemption of Chriſt a cover for all licentiouſneſſe, and fleſhly liberty, and ſay they are to that end redeemed; which redemption the Son of God needed not to come from Heaven to purchaſe for them; man being thither fallen, by nature ſubject thereto; but all who know the redemption of Chriſt, by his pretious blood, are redeemed from the vaine Converſation received by tradition, into the holy converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5, 18.</note> of him that hath called them, to be holy as he is holy, and not vain as the World is vain<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And this is the true redemption to all that know it whereby this ſeed hath received redemption for us, who were transgreſſors, even to purge the conſcience from dead works to ſerve<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heh.</hi> 9. 12, 15.</note> the Living God. And for this end he gave himſelf for us to redeeme<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 14.</note> us from all iniquity and purify unto himſelf a peculiar people zealous of<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev</hi> 5 9.</note> of good works; who hath redeemed us to God by his blood out of<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 4.</note> kindreds, tongues, and faſhions, from amongſt men, to follow the the lamb and not the luſt. And all whoſe redemption leads not out of this world, will fail you when you look for another, and this all that are redeemed know; but who live in the luſt are blinded with the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118947:34"/>
god thereof, as the light in every conſcience ſhall teſtifie, that he that lives to the fleſh is not redeemed.</p>
               <p>So with the light of Chriſt which lets you ſee your transgreſſions, ſearch your hearts, that you may ſee if the juſt principle that moves to righteouſneſſe be not oppreſſed, and burthened, and over-powred, by the ſeed of the evill doer, and that nature which loves carnal delights; and ſo you be led captive to do the works of Satan; then what redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have you further then a talk? like a man that hath a conceit of eating, but ſtill hungry: ſo you conceit freedom, but ſtill ſerve ſin; and while ſervants of ſin, you are free from righteouſneſſe; as he that is a ſervant of righteouſneſſe is free from ſin; for it is an eaſie thing to conceit righteouſneſſe and redemption, but he that doth righteouſneſſe is righteous, even as he is righteous: but this is not ſeene while the ſeed of God is in bondage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning Juſtification, Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, and Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification.</head>
               <p>THe wiſdom of men in the Fall finding theſe ſeveral words in Scripture, hath in their imaginations run them into diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſeparated that which is in one, and cannot be devided in the poſſeſſion: for it is one that worketh all theſe, where he is preſent, according to the meaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. And this is the juſt one, who by faith lives in the Creature, and the Creature in him; and ſo becomes the juſtifier, and ſanctifier, of all that believe, and the mortifier of that nature which is out of the faith; and one of theſe is not alone without the reſt. For that which ſanctifies, that mortifies, and the ſame juſtifies, and all that know what it is to have theſe in the life, knows this.</p>
               <p>I know, there are a people who have a deſire to Heaven more then to holyneſſe, and they, leſt they ſhould ſpoyle their Carnal delights, have in their brain-imag'nation conceipted a Juſtification without ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification or mortification; wreſting thoſe Scriptures which condemns the works of the law, and therewith they would exclude the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of faith alſo. And becauſe the Scripture ſaith, God juſtifies the ungodly through faith, therefore they conclude themſelves juſtified in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:118947:34"/>
their ungodlineſſe by a fancy which they call faith, but are without faith in Chriſt: For that faith which laies not hold upon Gods righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is not the faith of Chriſt, but a dead thing: for ſo far as any hath the faith of Chriſt, ſo far it reveals Gods righteouſneſſe without the law, from faith to faith; by which righteouſneſſe of God, the juſt lives and the unjuſt dies; and ſo juſtified, as they are ſanctified, and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, and no further: even as the righteouſneſſe of God without the law is manifeſt, being witneſſed by the Law; and the Prophets, even the righteouſneſſe of God, which is by faith of Jeſus Chriſt unto all, and upon all that beleive, without reſpect of perſons. No righteouſneſſe, no faith in Chriſt, but where Gods righteouſneſſe is unto all and upon all, there the belief is witneſſed; and the faith is ſhewed by the works which cannot be ſhewed without the works: for that faith that hath not works is dead being alone; as the body without the Spirit, ſo is your faith without workes; and ſo is your juſtification, without holineſſe, and mortification of life. And you will find in the end, that he that juſtifies the wicked in you, is the ſame that condemneth the juſt, and they are both abomination to the Lord: And this is your ſtate who plead for ſin, and live in pleaſure, and wantonly on the earth: you ſlay the juſt, and holy one, and ſave the unjuſt alive; and ſo know not him that is juſt; who juſtifies, mortifies, ſanctifies and redeemes; who of God is made ſo to us, that, in all things we are and have, we may glory in him.</p>
               <p>And although the Scriptures mention theſe three, yet not to devide them ſo, as to make people believe they may have one and not all; but as to ſhew the ſeverall effects of that one work of mans redemption, all wrought by one thing in the creature, For the blood of Chriſt it waſhes away the filth, and ſo puts off the old man, and mortifies the deeds of that body, and ſo ſanctifies, and juſtifies: The Spirit it morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, and ſanctifies, and juſtifies; now though the Saints named both theſe, it was not to devide them; but being one, they might declare it by either; for none could have the one without the other, and all that have them are thereby mortified, ſanctified, and juſtified; yet none of theſe without the creature, being works of faith, and not of ſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for by the law of faith is ſelfe-ſanctification, ſelf-mortification, and ſelf-juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, excluded, though they who had received the Spirit were called to all theſe by faith in his blood, yet it is the work of God wrought by Chriſt in the believer, and in the light are they called to behold the work of God herein, and joyne to it in the faith and obedience thereto, being the work of God, which he will work in all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive in the light, that they may receive his Son, in whom the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is, and the power to mortification, ſanctification, and juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as by faith he is received, from the dead, who was delivered for our offences, and raiſed againe for our juſtification: but ſuch who would ſhare in his Juſtification, but not have fellowſhip in his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and obedience are ſuch as are juſtified in conceipt, but ſin raignes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:118947:35"/>
and the unjuſt lives and acts in them; and this is ſelfe that juſtifies ſelfe, but is not juſt before God, the juſt being dead in treſpaſſes and ſins; but God juſtifies the living and not the dead: Therefore the Saints ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the loſſe of all things, counting them as doung that they might know him, and the power of his reſurrection, and the fellowſhip of his ſufferings being made conformable to his death; Theſe through death came to the power and fellowſhip of his reſurrection, whereby they are juſtified, being raiſed with him to newneſſe of life; by faith receiving the gift of Gods righteouſneſſe, and becoming ſervants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and thereby became free from ſin; and this is true juſtification, where there is no condemnation, where the deeds of the fleſh are mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, and the creature walks no more after the fleſh but after the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: for the condemnation is to him that walks after the fleſh, but he<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 16.</note> that walks in the Spirit is juſtified: for he that walks in the Spirit ſhal not<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8, 3, 4</note> fulfill the luſts of the fleſh, and there is mortification to that nature that breaks the law; and the juſt is ſeen who fulfils the law, in ſuch as walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit. So not the hearers of the law are juſt<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 2, 13.</note> before God, but the doers of the law ſhall be juſtified. In the firſt mans ſtate the law is broken, and there mortification, and ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is denyed; and there the man would be juſtified from the guilt of ſin; but not from the love and power of ſin, but would have his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall delights in the world and Heaven alſo, but this is vaine hope, and will periſh: But in the ſecond mans ſtate, the law is fulfilled, through mortification, ſanctification, Juſtification of the Spirit. And no man can be juſtified where the juſt lives not; for that by which the juſt lives, is that by which the creature is juſtified.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning the Law.</head>
               <p>IN this thing are many people confounded, yea all who know not the miniſtration of the Spirit; for ſuch going into the Scriptures and finding the miniſtration of the Letter, and the miniſtration of the Spirit, and themſelves being under neither of theſe, but in Notion, as they have received it in their imaginations, and not from the Mouth of the Lord, ſome ſay they are under the Law, and that it continues ſtill; others ſay, but ſome part of it which is Morall; others ſay, nay but it is done away, and they are not under any miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Law, but under grace, and ſo by their faith make voyd the Law, not knowing what they ſay herein. And this is all ſuch know, either of Law or Goſpel, who in their wiſdom and prudence read the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:118947:35"/>
letter, and from thence imagine what is Law, and what is Grace, not having that ſpirit by which they were miniſtred to the Saints, and by them received, who had the law in their hearts, and grace there alſo; and ſuch do know that the one of theſe doth not make voyd the other, but eſtabliſh the other; for the coming of Chriſt was not to make voyd but to fulfill the Law; and he doth not come to put the Law afatre off but to bring it neare, that with his light all may ſee it, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the heart, by the living God; and he is ſo farre from deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or taking away the Law, that he declares it in its force and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſaying, That one jot or tittle ſhould not paſſe till it be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled.</p>
               <p>And whereas it was ſaid in the letter, Thou ſhalt not commit adultery, ſaith he, Thou ſhalt not luſt: In the letter it was ſaid thou ſhalt not ſweare falſely, but in the Spirit, he ſaith, Swear not at all: In the letter, Thou ſhalt not kill, but in the Spirit, Thou ſhalt not be angry; and whoſoever doth any of theſe things is guilty before God, and this is farre from making it voy'd which declares it in its purity, ſo as they who might ſeeme to be cleare in the letter, might be found guilty in the Law of the Spirit; that by Chriſt Jeſus who is the end of that Law, they may come to ſee their condemnation; and by faith in him become ſet free, not by the blood of Bulls, and Goats, and the aſhes of an Heifer, and carnall Sacrifices, Oracle, Temple, or Altar, or Days, or Sabbaths without, in the letter; but by all theſe in Spirit; which are in Chriſt Jeſus miniſtred to the ſoule, and conſcience, to waſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſin, and purge the conſcience from dead works to ſerve the living God; which the miniſtration of the letter, and carnall Ordinances could not do.</p>
               <p>And for this cauſe is the miniſtration of the letter done away, becauſe it could not make perfect the commers thereto, as pertaining to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; And the Miniſtration of the Spirit preached in its ſteed, which gives perfect knowledge of ſin, and perfect redemption from it, and from all things from which the Law without, could not, and the ſame Spirit doth teſtifie it perfectly in the conſcience, which the letter can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not: though the letter may ſhew a man his condemnation, yet it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give life, it can ſhew the duty but not give power to performe it; ſo the letter kils, but the Spirit giveth life.</p>
               <p>And hence it is that all you who read your duty in the letter, but want power to performe what you read, you ſet up your imaginations inſtead of performance: and ſome ſay the Law is done away, and none now ſhall be condemned by it; others ſay Chriſt fulfilled it in his own perſon, and to believe what he did ſixteene hundred yeares ſince is all we need to do; others ſay, nay but we muſt do what we can of what the Scriptures commands, and he will do the reſt, with his Father; others ſay, that what we do he makes it accepted which the Father, as though we did performe all that is required; but none in that ſtate knows his commands in Spirit, which gives life and power to performe what is
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:118947:36"/>
commanded in Spirit, which none knows who reads what others did, but want their Spirit and power to performe the ſame; This was the ſelfe righteouſneſſe and is the ſelfe righteouſneſſe, which is by the letter of the Law taken-on without the Spirit of life, which is in Chriſt Jeſus. And here is the weakneſſe of the Law taken-on through the fleſh; but the power of the law, to ſuch as receive it in Spirit, and life: for the Law is fulfilled in Spirit and not in the letter, and ſo in Chriſt and not in ſelfe; and ſo by faith, and not by works; even by the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing righteouſneſſe of God, freely given and received by faith, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the creature from faith to faith in every one that beleives, and not by works of the Law which the creatures ſee in the letter, and ſets themſelves a doing, who are carnall, and ſold under ſin, not quickened by the Spirit of righteouſneſſe: for the letter of the Law gives the knowledge of ſinne; but the Law in the Spirit gives not only the knowledge of ſin; he knowledg of God, and his righteouſneſſe in Chriſt Jeſus for fulfilling the Law, which is life eternall, according to his promiſe, I will write my Law in your hearts, and put it in your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts, and you ſhall all know me from the greateſt to the leaſt; ſo the letter kills but the Spirit giveth life.</p>
               <p>So all you who read the commands in the letter without, from thence you may fetch your own Condemnation, but from thence can you not fetch power for obedience, to juſtification of life. From within is the Life, in Spirit, and not in the letter. And here is change of the Law to that which is Spirituall, the Preiſthood Spirituall; The Temple Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual; The Altar, the Circumciſion, the offering, the blood, the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, the Anointing, the waſhings, and the whole worſhip, which was without, and could make nothing perfect, is become Spirituall; and within; which is the better hope, being more pure then that without could be; and ſo more perfect even as he is perfect. Now the Law was added becauſe of transgreſſion till the promiſed ſeed ſhould come, of whom it is propheſied in types, and figures; which ſeed is Chriſt the end of the Law to every one that believes, without reſpect of perſons; and ſo it is in the ſpirit. A Law hath God written in the heart, whereby the transgreſſor is condemned in his own Conſcience, and this Law is upon the firſt Man, who is the Transgreſſor, and hath power over that man as long as he lives; Judging, reproving, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; And propheſying of one that is to come to fulfill the Law in every one who minds the light; And ſo is as a Scool-maſter to bring to Chriſt: And till he come to fulfill it, who is the end of it, there is Condemnation upon the Creature; becauſe the pure Law of God is broken; And this is teſtified by the light in the conſcience, a witneſſe againſt the firſt Man and his deeds, which is contrary to the perfect Law of God; And ſo by that which perfect is he condemned who is imperfect, where the Image of God is loſt, and the ſeed lyes in death, becauſe of treſpaſſes and ſins.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:118947:36"/>For God did not give a Law to condemne his own work, but the work of the Devil. And where the transgreſſor is, there is the work of the Devil. And the law hath power over that man as long as the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor lives. And all his works are by the law condemned, untill the Reſurrection of the ſeed, and the Image of God be witneſſed, and all things ſubdued to him, who is the end of the Law, by whom the fruits of the Spirit are brought forth, againſt which there is no Law. And ſo by his reſurrection, and the vetrue thereof, that which is of God in the Conſcience is anſwered; And ſo the creature ſaved from the condemnation of the Law of God which reſpects no mans perſon; But hath reſpect to his own ſeed, where it is raiſed, but condemns all where it lyes in death, and where death raigns.</p>
               <p>So the Law that layes hold upon all trangreſſors we witneſſe to endure ſpirituall, juſt, and good; Given forth againſt the firſt Man, and his works good or bad, (as people calls them,) yea though he ſet himſelf to do the workes of the Law never ſo zealouſly, yet a witneſſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation the pure Law of God is againſt him in his conſcience, untill the promiſed ſeed be born which is not of the will of the firſt Man, nor after the fleſh; but after the ſpirit, after the will of God (one with the Law) and by his grace, who ſhews the merry and glad tydings.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the fleſh who received the law in the literall Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the carnall ordinances of them, was Chriſt to be born; who was made of a woman, under the law to redeeme them that was under the law if they did beleive: Even ſo now <hi>Iſrael</hi> fater the Spirit, who receive the law in the Spirituall miniſtration written in the heart, ſuch ſhall witneſſe the Child Born of the Royall ſeed, heir of the promiſe even of Gods righteouſneſſe, for the fulfilling of the pure Law of God, for that end given forth; Whereof there are many witneſſes at this day, who have patiently waited, in what God hath written in their hearts, ſeen with the light of Chriſt; Who have therein received the faith of the Goſpel, and the end of that faith, even Gods righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe revealed from faith to faith, whereby the pure law of God is fulfilled in many, and fulfilling in others, who abide in their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of faith which God hath dealt to them, walking in the Light, not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit: And ſo by the Law of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of life, which is in Chriſt Jeſus, ſee themſelves ſet free from the law of ſin and death; And ſo witneſſe the Goſpel, which you cannot do, who caſt the law of God, and his Light behind your backs, and in your vain minde ſay you are not under it; in the day of tryal, you will be found under the Condemnation thereof; And that in every con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall witneſſe thereto, at that day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:118947:37"/>
               <head>Concerning Chriſt Jeſus.</head>
               <p>THis is He whom the world much talk of, but few there be that know him, though it be He by whom all things were made, who is the Life of all Creatures, the Beginning of all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who was before all Creatures, without Beginning of Dayes, or End of Life, a Prieſt for ever, and a King, of whoſe Dominion there is no end: By him Kings reign, and Dominions are caſt down, though they know him not where Self is ſtanding, who is hidden from the worlds wiſdome, and the depth of Prudence cannot find him out; yet doth he reveal himſelf to ſuch as walk in his light, which is contrary to all the dark paths of the world, nor can the will of man walk therein; but who deny themſelves, that they may learn the way of the Lord, to ſuch he freely reveals his way for their return, that he may bring them down from the ſeat of exaltation, and make known to them their beginning, and from whence they are digged; that they may ſee him that bears up the pillars of the earth, &amp; hath laid the foundation thereof; who hath ſet the world in their hearts, who ſtood not in his counſell: ſo that they cannot find out the beginning, nor the end of the work of <hi>God;</hi> yet will vain man in that ſtate be imagining touching him, and from whence he had his beginning, who is the Eternal Word, before all time, glorified in the Heavens with the Father, who in time was manifeſt; which Word became fleſh, and dwelt amongſt us, and took upon him the form of a ſervant, and was made in the likeneſſe of men; and being found in faſhion as a man, he humbled himſelf, and became obedient to the death, that he might become a living Example to all Generations, which no Creature could be, the whole Creation being in the Fall; and having finiſhed the Work of Redemption, given him of the Father to do, and for which he was begotten, he aſcended far above all Heavens, to prepare a place for all that follow him by Faith in his Light; and that from thence all ſuch as wait for him, may ſee his appearance as a Saviour; and onely ſuch know him for their Redeemer, who know him for their Judge, and Law-giver, who love him, and keep his Commands; to ſuch he comes, and the Father alſo, and make their abode with him.</p>
               <p>And this is He who is the Light of the world, and lighteth every man that comes into the world; who ſtands at the door and knocks, and if any hear his voyce and open, he will come in and ſup with him; and ſuch know him, and he knows them who hear his voyce, by which they are
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:118947:37"/>
quickned out of the treſpaſſes and ſins, and the Seed of God raiſed out of death: but where Death reigns, Chriſt is rejected, and the wiſdome by which he ſhould be known is fooliſhneſſe.</p>
               <p>So, if you deſire to know him who is not of this world, but who is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world was, a Witneſſe againſt all the worlds wayes and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then mind that light in you which thus witneſſeth; for as Chriſt is, ſo is his light that leads to him; for that which bears teſtimony againſt the world, is not of the world, even as he is not of the world, and ſo leads out of the world, to him who is not known in the world: for the world by wiſdome knows him not. And as thou follows the light out of the world, thou wilt come to ſee the ſeed, which by the worlds wiſdome and glory is crucified; to which Seed are all the Promiſes, and wherein is all the knowledge of God and Chriſt: and as that Seed is raiſed, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is the Father revealed, and his Power and God-head, in his Son Jeſus Chriſt, which in him dwels, and without him is not revealed; but being known, is Life Eternal, and Eternal Power, and Eternal Glory, and Riches, made manifeſt in the Light: for as you know this Seed raiſed by the ſame Spirit, that raiſed Jeſus Chriſt from the death; ſo ſhall you ſee him to whom all power and judgment is committed in Heaven and Earth; and for whom, and by whom, all things were made in Heaven and Earth: of whom it is ſaid, When he bringeth his onely begotten Son into the world, Let all the Angels worſhip him; who maketh his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels Spirits, and his Miniſters a flame of fire; whoſe Fleſh is the Life of Men, and his Light is as a Law that goeth forth, whereby man is led to his food, and the ſons of men ſees out of darkneſſe; and this is he who cannot be limitted, nor his perſon reſtrained in one place, who filleth Heaven and Earth with his preſence, and appeareth at his pleaſure to his own; (though the wiſe of the world knows him not, and therefore limit him above the ſtars) who dwelleth in the bodies of his Saints; but as for the Reprobates, they know him not ſo, who have put the good day farre from them, and hate reproof, that they may ſpend their days in folly, and feed themſelves with the wind, and fill their hearts with carnal delights. When the hearts of the Children of Light are eſtabliſhed with grace: yet theſe will be diſputing about the body of Chriſt; but the body of ſinne rules in them, whereby they are darkened and become Heart-blind, paſt<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4. 18, 19.</note> feeling the meaſure of God, whoſe hearts are over-charged with ſurfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and cares of the world, and their minds corrupted with Earthly things.</p>
               <p>To ſuch I ſay, Ceaſe your imaginations, as to find out what Chriſt is in that ſtate, for he alone reveals himſelf in Spirit, to ſuch as wait in the Light, and love that which is pure; to ſuch his appearance is as the Sun, whoſe Riſing is not by the Will of Man; but for his appearing all the World muſt wait, to be refreſhed with the Beams of his Glory, and to all who are yet in the night ſhall he appear, if you look towards the place of his Riſing; which is not, Lo here, Lo there; but within you in your<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 17. 21.</note> hearts: and all who are come to the ſure Word of Propheſie, as to a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:118947:38"/>
Light that ſhines in a dark place, to which you do well to take heed, til the day dawn, and the Day-ſtar ariſe in your hearts you ſhall ſee the Sun ariſe where the day-ſtarr appeares in your hearts if in the light you wait that ſhines in the darkneſſe: and you ſhall feel the vertue and life of him, and receive thereof to live in the ſame with him; and you ſhall ſee him as he is, and know him to be the Sun of Righteouſneſſe, whoſe ariſing is, with healing in his wings; and whoſe breaking forth is upon all his enemies which over the ſeed hath raigned; whoſe ſpirituall weapons are mighty through God to the palling down ſtrongs holds, caſting down imaginations, and every high thing that exalteth it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God, and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of himſelf, and having in readineſſe to revenge all diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience when your obedience is fulfilled.</p>
               <p>And thus the Saints know the Son, with his Light, his power, and dominion over all things in Heaven and in Earth; who rules in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe in the hearts of his people, trampling down Satan under their feet, which Son of God Hypocrites call Lord Lord, but the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, they ſerves and obey; and though ſuch have got the words of Lord, and Chriſt, and Jeſus, yet they know not his light, his power, his kingdom, and dominion, over ſin and the Devill in them, to ſet them free therefrom, by his Light and life; Nor his blood to waſh them from their pollutions, and to preſent them without ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing. And ſo you have made the name of Chriſt a reproach among the Nations; who call him a redeemer, but lives in your ſins, So as ſuch as profeſſe not the ſyllables of Chriſt and Jeſus, even from a principle of God within them, many of them become your Judges, as to moderation, faithfullneſſe, and honeſty.</p>
               <p>Nay it is manifeſt amongſt you, that the name of Jeſus which gives the Saints victory over ſin, you know not; Who have it in words and therewith make a cover for your ſin, your pride, Luſt, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. What covetouſneſſe, and all manner of unrighteouſneſſe is covered over which a profeſſion of the Name of Chriſt, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deems from thoſe things all that knows him; For none knowes Jeſus further then they know a Saviour from ſin; And not a cover for ſin, and live in it; for the promiſe of the Father is, He ſhall ſave his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from their ſins. And the Children of the promiſe knowes this to be ſo, without a cover or meaning to live in ſin. And none knowes Chriſt but who knowes the anointing, and ſuch need no man to teach them, but as the Anointing teacheth them all things that is true, if they abide therein, and there is noe lye in it.</p>
               <p>But who ſayes they know Chriſt, and are redeemed; and commits ſin, not keeping his commands, is a lyer; And ſo abides not in the truth and anointing; And ſo is of the Devil and not of Chriſt; for he that abides in Chriſt, ſins not; For the Name of Jeſus Chriſt is pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over all ſin, as it is known, and the creature baptized into it by faith. So all that know Chriſt, know the ſeed, the promiſe, the word of Life, the covenant, the Heritage, the righteouſneſſe, the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:118947:38"/>
Kingdom, the power, the glory which is not of this world, and the Father of all: which you that commits ſin have not ſeen. Neither can any ſay that Jeſus is Lord but by the Spirit, ſo you whoſe knowledge is without, Another Lord ruleth within.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concerning the Miniſtry of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>THe Miniſters of Chriſt are ever Called out of the World and contrary to the world, contrary to their own wills and the wills of all fleſh, for ſuch have the Word who are begotten of the word, and ſuch are begotten contrary to the will of man, and through ſuch came the Scriptures which came not by the will of man, but by the Spirit, and ſo are of no private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, nor are his miniſters of any private Call, but of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who hath all creatures in his hand, to chuſe whom he will, to go on his meſſage, nor would he ever ſend by whom the Kings of the earth did chuſe, nor the powers thereof, but ſuch as they called and ſet up without his Immediate call, was ever the great enemies to ſuch as he ſent, and this is evident in all the Scriptures and in all hiſtories ſince, that when ever the myſtery of iniquity had ſpread over, and darkneſſe had paſſed over his ſeed, and his people had broken his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and loſt his word, then he in love to his people ſent out ſome Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately who had his word in them to bear witneſſe to the Lord againſt all their blackſlidings and ſelf wayes and formall worſhips, and to ſuch the worlds miniſters, or rather maſters, was ever enemies, and ſought to ſtirr up the powers of men againſt them to devour them, alwayes under the name of Blaſphemers and hereticks &amp; deſtroyers of worſhip and peace-breakers, and enemies to authority when they are but ſent of God to teſtifie againſt their falſe worſhips, and to break the peace of the wicked one, who keeps his houſe in peace till a ſtronger then he comes. And this you ſhall find recorded through all the Scriptures: And all hiſtories, of perſecution in all ages and at this day: and you ſhall never find that ever any of theſe could joyn in with the worlds wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips but cryed them down, their prieſts, their prophets, their dayes, their times, their places, their whole worſhip who was gone out into the world from the Word and ſpirit, for which they was ever envied of them who was therein and ſuch as they had deceived thereby, for the world ever loves its own, but he that is of God teſtifies againſt the world
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:118947:39"/>
and the deeds thereof that they are evil, therefore hated thereby, for the truths ſake.</p>
               <p>And as the miniſters of Chriſt are ever Called out of the world and the things thereof, ſo they are not carfull for the things of the world, but he who is their maſter is their maintainer, whom they preach; and ſo they that preach the Goſpel live of the Goſpel, ſo never any of his ſought to the people for meanes, nor bear rule by it, nor ſought for their gain from their quarter, nor taught for the fleece, preached for hire nor propheſied for money, for peices of bread, nor handfulls of Corn, none of Chriſt miniſters ever lived in parſon ages, nor lived upon tythes, nor ever went to law with their flock for carnall things, they were never called maſters of their hearers but ſervants, they were never approved by men to whom they was to preach, but was ſent of God to preach to ſuch as ſought him not, nor them neither, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſuch they in all things approving themſelves to be miniſters of God, (that the miniſtry be not blamed,) In much patience, in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in neceſſities, in diſtreſſes, in Stripes, in priſonments, in tumults, in labors, in watchings, in faſtings, by pureneſſe; by knowledge, by longſuffering, by kindneſſe, by the holy Ghoſt, by love unfained, by the word of truth, by the power of God, by the armor of righteouſneſſe on the right hand and on the left; by honour and diſhonour, by evil report and good report, as deceivers and yet true, as unknown, yet well known, as dying yet live, chaſtned, ſorrowfull, poor, having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, wandering up and down, having no certain dwelling place, and in this ſtate their reward was, that they might keep the Goſpel without Charge, and yet they was ever hated by ſuch as was approved of men who ſtirred up ſuch as they preached to for their hire, to perſecute them that preached freely, yet muſt they not ceaſe but preach freely; even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their own wills; to ſuch as are ſo far from hiring them, as they would rather devour them then heare them, yet will hire and heare them of their own chooſings: And this muſt be that the grace of God may apeare to be free, and He be found of them that ſought him not.</p>
               <p>And this was ever his way who will be taught by none, nor ſhall any chuſe for him, by whom he ſhall ſend, nor ſhall any whom he ſends ever want, nor take care for ought afore-hand, that they may follow their maiſter, and be as their Lord, who ſhall feed many, but ſeek to none for food, but what God gives: for it is not like that they ſhould feed others with everlaſting food, who dare not truſt God for carnall food for God will not have ſuch as are of his family to take care for food: or Raiment, nor wherewith to feed others, for who hath the word in them, in which all fullneſſe is, need not ſtudy what to ſay, nor have a divination to make; what to preach, like them who have not the word in them, but what they ſteal from another, or fetch out of the bottomleſſe pit by divination and witchcraft, who can have their word in their own times and wills, againſt whom they will, and to flatter whom they will, who cry peace to ſuch as put into their mouthes, elſe they prepare warr againſt them,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:118947:39"/>
who minde earthly things; whoſe God is their belly, who talke againſt pride and live in it, againſt covetouſneſſe and live in it, who preach againſt ſin but cannot ceaſe from ſin: and ſuch as they are, ſuch is their hearers, who in words confeſſe Chriſt, but in works deny him; And theſe are they who for their pride pleaſures and carnall ends, have changed all the Lords worſhip from what it was both in matter manner meanes and maintenance, and ſo have ſcattered the Lords people into ſects and opinions, Forms, Cuſtomes and Traditions, in every Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as may beſt ſute their wicked wills; for which they pretend de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency order and neceſſity, ſo that not one is found in the way of God, nor forme of true worſhip ſuch as the Scriptures will own, without wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And now the Lord is appeared in the true way as Chriſt left it with his diſciples to gather his own from off all theſe mountaines where they are ſcattered, all the Idol ſhepards are gathering againſt him to bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, of all ſorts, not willing to heare of the living way, which is but one, in which there is no Rent, Sect, Error, and opinion, but Chriſt in all, nay one can ſcarcely grieve a Town-Teacher, worſe then to tell him of the Apoſtles way of preaching, their call, their ſpirit, their wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings, their wages, their word, and way of walking in this world, and amongſt their hearers, as is declared in Scripture without a meaning, or liberty to change it according to the times.</p>
               <p>Nay, though all their pariſh be beleivers (as they call them) yet can they not beleive they ſhall get their wages from them without a law to compell them, ſo that though they have begott a larger faith in their hearers then the Apoſtles ever taught; (to wit) that though they commit ſin while they live, yet they may be ſaved and ſet free when they dye, yet have not they ſo much faith themſelves as to beleive, they will pay them their wages, without it be forced from them, that which none of Chriſts Miniſters ever did either in Law or Goſpel, ſo we may not ſay that theſe are Miniſters of Chriſt, or like them, if we will ſpeak truth and take Chriſts Rule to judge by, who ſaith, By their fruits you ſhall know them.</p>
               <p>Nor ſhould I have ſpoken thus much of them in this place, did they but call themſelves the miniſters of men, made ſo by them, and ſo upholden, and maintained; but ſuch as call themſelves miniſters of Chriſt and walk ſo far unlike him and his in all things, I ſay, to ſuch as are found in theſe things; Your wayes teſtifie to your face and before all men, that you are no more like the miniſters of Chriſt then they that walked in your ſteps before you: ſo Search the ſcriptures, and ſearch your hearts with the light of Chriſt, and know your portion, and count me not your enemy for telling you the truth, how ever I have cleared my conſcience in love to your ſoules though ſuch as are deceived, through blind zeal and enviy cannot receive it,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:118947:40"/>
               <head>Concerning Free—Will.</head>
               <p>THere is no Will free for God, but that which is free from ſinne; which Will Man loſt in the Fall, when he let in the Will of the Devil, and entred into it; wherein Man became in bondage. And all that man, in that ſtate, knows of the free Will, is that which moves in him, againſt the Will of the fleſh, and of the Devil, which is ſeen in the Light of Chriſt. And this is the Will of God, whereby he willeth not the death of the ſinner. And this Will of God is manifeſt, according to the Spirit which is free, always moving contrary to the Will of the fleſh, which is in bondage to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. And this Will that is free, onely thoſe who abide in the light, do feel the moving of it preſent, in the Spirit; And as the Spiritual man is quickned by the Word of God, and that man born which is not of the fleſh, nor of the will of it; ſo is that Will ſeen again in man which is free, wherein the Creature is made free from the Will of the fleſh, which is bondage. So, the Spiritual man hath the Spiritual Will which is free; and that is from above: And the Carnal man which is from below, his Will keeps in bondage, who is contrary to God in all things. So the firſt born hath not the Free-Will, for who is born after the fleſh thereof is kept in bondage; but who is begotten again of the Word from above, is free born, (when he is born) who is born of the Spirit; for where the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord is, there is liberty; but where the Spirit of the World is, there is bondage: for as is the Man, ſo is his Will: So with the light of Chriſt which ſhows you the thoughts of the heart, if you it diligently mind, you may ſee the two motions of the two Wills, each contrary to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: the one, after the fleſh: the other, after the ſpirit: So whether of theſe Wills thou art ſervant to, that thou may be ſaid to have; and to the other thou art an enemy, for no man hath Free-Will further then he is joyned to it, though he that is in his own Will may feel the Will of God contrary to him, and that Will he is in; yet can he not come to it, untill he own that which leads him to take up the Croſs to his firſt Will, and in the Croſs to his own Will is he born, who hath the Will of God, wherein God worketh to Will, and to do of his good pleaſure, in the Male and in the Female, even the plant of God, who hath the will of God, the mind of God, the heart of God, as in meaſure he is formed it the Creature. So man hath not free will further then he is free-bor
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118947:40"/>
from above of the Seed that ſinneth not, and the growth in that Seed is mans freedom; but while this lies under the Earthly Will, and Self, thereby it is denied, though the Free-will may often move in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to Holineſs, and be felt in the light of Chriſt as a Tender of healing; yea, and would lead to holineſs &amp; healing, were it minded &amp; obeyed, for that will which is of God, onely leads to God; by which Will we are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified and ſaved: but you that ſtand in the Will of the fleſh, reſiſts, and ſo you will not come to me, that you may have life; for the Will of God which is life, is free, and freely tendered in Chriſt Jeſus to every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and in the light, which reproves the evil deeds it is ſeen; but they that reſiſt free grace, reſiſt free will; for thats free grace which ſhews a man his ſin, and reproves for it, which would lead to God, and to deny all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and ſo to live godlily, righteouſly, and ſoberly in this evill world. And thats free Will, which wills not that thou ſhould commit ſin; which Will is, that thou ſhould not die: So mans deſtruction is of himſelf, and ſelf-will, by which he reſiſts the Will of God; but Salvation is of the Will of God which is free, and in the meaſure of God is this freedom found and enjoyed: ſo that in Chriſt I have free will; but in the fleſh is bondage: therefore the fleſh muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by all that will own freedom in will or deed; for none hath free Will but who in the light of Chriſt hath learned to deny their own Wills; and ſuch knows, that in the firſt man is neither will nor deed that is free from ſin, nor for God, and his Work, or Worſhip: for God hath conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the whole man under ſin, that the gift of grace might appear to be free, that all might glory in the Lord, and the whole treaſure be found in him, to whom every tongue ſhall confeſs, when the glory of man ſhall come to an end, to his praiſe, who is bleſſed for evermore.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
